<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The flaming bush. Or, An embleme of the true Church. Written by Thomas Westerne, minister of Gods Word at Alderleigh in Cheshire</title>
            <author>Westerne, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854888</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1047:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The flaming bush. Or, An embleme of the true Church. Written by Thomas Westerne, minister of Gods Word at Alderleigh in Cheshire</title>
                  <author>Westerne, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 108, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last two leaves are blank except for marginal rules.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Flaming Buſh. <hi>OR,</hi> AN EMBLEME OF THE TRVE CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>Written by THOMAS WESTERNE, Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Alderleigh</hi> in CHESHIRE.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Spirat Rubus aſper Amomum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20343:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20343:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE RIGHT NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE Gentleman, Mr. THOMAS STANLEY of <hi>Alderleigh</hi> Eſquire, all health and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Wine needes no Buſh, a good face no band: but groſe Wine a Buſh to vent it: a courſe face a band to grace it. Were my lines polite they neede leſſe Patronage, but ſuch they are that they want tutelage. The old Romans had their tutelar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gods,
<pb facs="tcp:20343:3"/> but they by them rob'd God of his honour: be you to be a tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar god, <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. I haue ſayd you are Gods.</note> (you may be hereafter a titular god) ſo God ſhall haue prayſe by this my labour. When <hi>Adam</hi> beheld his owne naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he ran to a Buſh to hide his follies: Now the World muſt view my many weakneſſes, I come to you to ſhelter my fraylties. But <hi>Adam,</hi> and I differ in this: He like a Wood-cocke thruſt his bill in a Buſh, to be kept cloſe from the eyes of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: I would be ſhrowded vnder your bowes to be kept dry from the ſtormes of Calumny. <hi>Adam</hi> might thinke that God would follow him: the Diuell I thinke (for detractors are <hi>Diuels</hi>) will follow me: if he do, your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous name on the front of this Pamphlet ſhall be a generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſme to coniure this ſpirit, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring
<pb facs="tcp:20343:3"/> him to more then Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorian ſilence. But ſilence: why ſhould I looke for any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, as that theſe nifles and trifles ſhould purchaſe your Countenance? Beleeue it Sir, the fault is yours, becauſe you haue beene benevolent, therfore am I growne impudent: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue that cauſe, the effect cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, if you reſtrayne your cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, I ſhall refrayne mine inſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lency; but your worſhip (as yet) hath not done the one, therefore am I preſumptuous in not doing the other.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>This flaming Buſh I do d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uote to you,</l>
               <l>Wherein the Churches portrait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re to view,</l>
               <l>I haue diſplayd, adorn'd with roote, and bole</l>
               <l>The Barke, the branches, leaues too of the ſoule,</l>
               <l>With ſoueraigne fruits. A ſecond task remaines</l>
               <l>Which God aſſiſting doth require my paines:</l>
               <l>Namely to ſhew how this our Buſh with fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Doth flame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as alwayes ſubiect to the ire</l>
               <l>Of Diuell, Pharoh, Turke, and mitred Pope</l>
               <l>Which would with faggot quite burne vp her</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20343:4"/>
               <l>And then a third, wherein ſhall be diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>How this our Buſh that in the fire is tride,</l>
               <l>Doth finde her Planter ſo benigne and kinde,</l>
               <l>That ſhe conſum'd is not, but more refinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>This the Platforme of this my building, it is no great <hi>edifice,</hi> onely three bayes: whereof the firſt you haue here in <hi>facto,</hi> alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reade; the other are in <hi>fieri,</hi> perhaps in ſquaring if the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be not diſcouraged: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer this is vented, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will of him that dwelt in the Buſh, dwell with you: he that was figured by the Ram in the Buſh, protect you, while I that haue laboured and beaten the Buſh will ſerue you</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>most obſequiouſly, obſeruantly: Tho. Weſterne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20343:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe the Prouerb ſayth, <hi>One Bird in the hand, is better then two in the Buſh;</hi> I haue preſented thee here both a Bird and a Buſh, and hauing two Birds in a Buſh, to catch for thee hereafter, one Bird in the hand I offer thee here: thou wilt ſay an Ouſel; be it ſo: yet if her feathers be blacke, her fleſh is reſtoratiue: Onely her war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling tunes expect thy cenſure, if they pleaſe, shee is pleas'd, for to this end shee ſings that thou might dance: If otherwiſe, had shee a tongue to ſpeake, shee would
<pb facs="tcp:20343:5"/> craue pardon: I that should teach her, am no good whiſtler; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the labour mine, ſo the fault mine: let gentleneſſe bee thine, as I will be thine, I hope well, (for I meane well) that thou wilt accept well, what it not done well.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <signed>T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20343:5"/>
            <head>THE Flaming Buſh.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EXOD. 3. VER. 2.</bibl>
               <q>And the Angell of the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto him in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lame of fire out of the midſt of a buſh: and he looked, and behold, the buſh burned with fire and the buſh was not conſumed.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ongſt all the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the booke of God there is none repleate with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, exhortation, imitation of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20343:6"/> precepts, vertues, then the <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateuch, or,</hi> 5. bookes of <hi>Moſes.</hi> As<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> my ſong ſhall be of mercy, and iudgement: heere mercy and iudgement are met together, truth and righteouſneſſe haue kiſſed each other. Iudgement, <hi>Adam</hi> ſinnes, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſweates: <hi>Eue</hi> ſins, <hi>Eue</hi> ſmarts: <hi>Serpent</hi> ſinnes, <hi>Serpent</hi> creepes: <hi>Cain</hi> ſins, <hi>Cain</hi> runnes: <hi>Noah</hi> ſinnes, <hi>Noah</hi> ſhames: the world ſinnes, the world ſwimmes: <hi>Sodom</hi> ſinnes, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> burnes: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſinnes, <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh</hi> drownes: <hi>Chorah</hi> ſinnes, <hi>Chorah</hi> ſinkes: <hi>Semper certa venit vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta, ſi ſint dilecta noſtra delicta.</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: The great Monarch of this great All, daigning to become all in all: a Taylour to <hi>Adam,</hi> a Saylour to <hi>Noah:</hi> a Pilot to <hi>Heber,</hi> a Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uan to <hi>Abraham,</hi> a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uoy to <hi>Iſacke,</hi> a ladder to <hi>Iacob,</hi> a chariot to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> a mid-wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Moſes,</hi> a leader<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> (oh thou that leadeſt <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> as a ſheepe) ſhe was the ſheepe, hee the ſheepheard that Iſrael might<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> ſing with the ſinger of Iſrael.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20343:6"/>
               <l>My Sheepheard is the liuing Lord, Nothing therefore I need:</l>
               <l>In paſtures fayre with waters calme, He ſets me for to feede.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Led them from Canaan where bread was wanting: Fed them in Egypt where food was abounding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bred them in <hi>Goſhen</hi> to numbers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding: till another King aroſe that knew nor <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> that knew not the indulgence they had by <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but knew to increaſe the afflictions of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph:</hi> it is rare to finde poſterity heire of his fathers charity. <hi>Dolor &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>inuicem cedunt; br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas:</hi> their <hi>Halcyon</hi> dayes are now at an end: mirth had preſented the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Scene, now ſorrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in to act her part. Iealous was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of<note place="margin">Exod. 1. 10</note> their multiplying powers, therefore makes policy his pyouer to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their ſtrength. Come let vs worke wiſely; as if Machia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>liſme<note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.</note> ſhould be chriſtened by the name of wiſedome. Taske-maſters are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20343:7"/> ouer Iſrael.</p>
            <p>They ſhould not bee Iſrael in this their perigration, did they not wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with God in many an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſuppoſed, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall working would coole their deſire, and power of begetting; as if, <hi>Sine Cerere, &amp; Baccho frigat ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Dum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur viuit. Naz' liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur inclu debantur ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debantur torqueban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicantur. Aug. de ciu. dei. l. 22. <hi>Exod. 1. 15.</hi>
               </note> but Gods vine is euer more fruitfull with bleeding palme, and Cammomill more fertile with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Then <hi>Shiprah,</hi> and <hi>Puah</hi> muſt be bloody <hi>Lucinas,</hi> to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their males as ſoone as they are borne: but though <hi>Miſraim</hi> be fleſht in <hi>Cain</hi>-like cruelty, their feminine hearts are ſuppled with mercy.</p>
            <p>Now the people muſt drowne whom the midwiues had ſpared,<note place="margin">Exod. 1. 22.</note> like bloody executors of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will; while the ſtreames of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> are the infants Sepulchers. <hi>Nilus</hi> was made white with bodies, bare bodyes of Innocents drowned: <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> was made to ſwell with teares, ſalt teares of mothers that mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <hi>Nilus</hi> was filled full of cryes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20343:7"/> of Fathers that lamented: Fathers, mothers, brothers, kinsfolks, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing for their babes, and would not be comforted, and would not be comforted becauſe they were not. In this perſecution <hi>Moſes</hi> was born;<note place="margin">Exod 2. 2.</note> the mother reioyces when a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child is borne, but quickly this ioy was Eclipſed with mone: hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide in Egypt with ſafety, nor reſide in <hi>Iochebeds</hi> arms with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but muſt bee expoſed to <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes</hi> mercy: where euery guſt is like to ouerwhelme him, and euery bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low like to ſwallow him. A cradle of bulruſhes is the babi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>boat, a bark of<note place="margin">Exod. 2. 3.</note> reedes the little ones ſhip, but God was the Pilot, Chriſt the maſt, faith the anchor, loue the ſayles, hope the tackling, confidence the decke, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee could not but arriue at a happy port. <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter came<note place="margin">Exod 2. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> foorth to waſh her in the coole ſtreames of <hi>Nilus</hi> to bath her, heard a cry, ſaw no creature, at laſt ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the precious casket, where beauty pleaded, and begd reliefe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20343:8"/> whilſt his mourneful Oratory pierc't her heart. Her heart was ſtruck with gentle compaſsion, yet her toung could ſay t'is an Hebrews child: yet this Hebrewes childe muſt bee her ſonne: he the ſonne, ſhee the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: onely there wanted a milkie nurſe, and who ſo fit a nurſe to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle him, as ſhe that felt ſuch throwes to beare him? (when we doe ſeeme moſt deiected, the prouidence of God is moſt declared.) No doubt, but oft the Lady did viſite him, as much reioycing when ſhee beheld him, nor Orphan-like did ſhee nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh him, but what court, or ſchoole could put into him, was duely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred. But who can waſh the Ethiops skin? or who can hide the Leopards ſpots? or make him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get hee was an Hebrew? though nurture often alienate nature, as <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus</hi> intimates in his Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an whelpes, here <hi>partus ſequitur ventrem,</hi> inſomuch as all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in Egypt could not weane <hi>Moſes</hi> from calling his nurſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20343:8"/> or winne him from willingly ſuffering with Iſrael. A good ſoule cannot but grieue with others, and haue a feeling Sympathie with its fellow members. He walkes forth and beholds their miſeries, and as he well can; reuenges their iniuries. An Hebrew, and a Gypſye are at contention, hee reſcues the Hebrew,<note place="margin">Exod. 2. 12, 13.</note> ſlayes the Egyptian. An Hebrew, and an Hebrew ſtriue together, (do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall broyles are fulleſt of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:) his courteous Rhetoricke can nothing win, behold an Egyptian in an Hebrewes skinne: a full veſſell muſt needs vent, a great heart muſt needs ſpeake, a turbulent ſtomacke cannot ſtay: wilt thou kill me as thou didſt the Egyptian the other day? oh with what impatient paſſion<note place="margin">14.</note> doth a galled heart receiue admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Then did <hi>Moſes</hi> flye into <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">15:</note> 
               <hi>Caelum mutat, non mutat ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> change of ſoyle doth not change the ſoule, but a man that is good, in euery place will bee doing good: <hi>Quis enim celauerit ignem?</hi> If
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20343:9"/> he cannot yet free the Iſraelites from <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> he will ayde the wronged<note place="margin">Exod. 2. 17.</note> daughters of <hi>Iethro:</hi> they attend their ſheepe and come to water them, the ruder ſhepheards keepe the water from them: a curriſh mind and chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh diſpoſition, hath no reſpect of ſex or condition. <hi>Moſes</hi> perceiues them the weaker veſſells, therefore thruſts himſelfe betwixt them and dangers, and by his vndaunted va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and magnanimity, aſſures, and ſecures them from the Shepheards inhumanity. Their olde Father is quickly told it, and with hoſpitall welcome entertaines him for it: and being a great and wealthy peere ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits<note place="margin">Exod. 2. 21.</note> him his ſeruant, adopts, makes him his ſonne in law, and ſends him abroad to follow his ſheepe. Now he that in Egypt followed his book, in <hi>Midian</hi> betakes himſelfe to his hooke. <hi>Moſes</hi> his hooke, as <hi>Peters</hi> net, <hi>Pauls</hi> tent, and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> rule may miniſter to vs this ſhort inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that neither greatneſſe nor<note place="margin">Note.</note> goodneſſe neede to bee aſhamed of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20343:9"/> an honeſt vocation. Forty yeares in Egypt a Courtier, and forty yeares in Midian a Shepheard; a ſolitary life, yet he likes it, a melancholy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet he continues it. He was not ignorant of Court-cares, that <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lae culmen ſublime lubricum,</hi> hee that climbes the higheſt, falles the ſooneſt, therefore a priuate, and retyred life in a higher degree doth more content<note place="margin">Note.</note> him. Hee that hath true worth in himſelfe, and outward, or inward fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with God, findes more pleaſure in a Midian wildernes, then others delight in Princely Pallaces.</p>
            <p>While innocent <hi>Moſes</hi> followes, and tends his innocent lambs, God doth graciouſly appeare to him viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; idle perſons are not graced with viſions: Idleneſſe is a cuſhion<note place="margin">Note.</note> whereon Satan ſits, where hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, or rather ſuggeſts manifolde temptations. God had beene euer preſent with <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet he had neuer ſeene him till now. When <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 3. 8.</note> did ill, hee would haue hid him in a Buſh: when <hi>Moſes</hi> did well, God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20343:10"/> is ſeene in a Buſh. A great wonder, in a ſmall matter: that a tender buſh ſhould burne with fire, was nothing marueilous, but that the fire ſhould not burne the buſh, was truely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous.</p>
            <p>A true Embleme of the true Church, and of euery true member of the Church.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Tis like a Buſh.</item>
               <item>2 A burning buſh.</item>
               <item>3 Yet it is no combuſtible buſh.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Church of God is reſembled to a Buſh.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In ſtature. quantity.</item>
               <item>2. In nature. quality.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>The Buſh is low: the Church is ſo</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>in others eyes.<note place="margin">1 Stature In other eyes.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>in it owne eyes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The worldling brandes it with markes of baſeneſſe: the Papiſt ſcornes it becauſe of the ſmallneſſe. In the worldlings eye, the Church is a buſh: the buſh is low; low, and<note place="margin">Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dling.</note> contemptible: the Church is baſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20343:10"/> baſe and deſpicable. <hi>Tune credis Chriſto? credis crucifixo?</hi> Was the common quaere in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time. What <hi>tu? Mecaenas atanis edite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus?</hi> Thou haſt beene of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port? thou who haſt borne a goodly port? wilt thou be ſtigmarized with the name of Chriſt? the ſhame of<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vita <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Chriſt? a new and wicked ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A Carpenters ſonne, a carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelfe, and <hi>ver dolorum,</hi> a man of ſorrowes; that had not ſo much as a houſe to be borne in, but bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed a ſtable: not a bed to be layd in but borrowed a manger: nor a pot to drink in, but borrowed a pitcher: nor an horſe to ride on, but borrowed an Aſſe: nor a roome to eate in, but borrowed a parlour: nor a graue to be buryed in, but borrowed a Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: thy Gods debaſement, will be thy diſparagement: being an offence to the Iewes, madneſſe to the Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, dotage vnto worldlings: a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious<note place="margin">Serres pag. 652. Aug. Coſ. lib. 11.</note> vermine (ſaide the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>) but (ſeditious Duke) good words we pray: <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud eſt ridere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20343:11"/> eſt videre,</hi> the naturall man ſees not the things of God, and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for he ſees naturally when the things of God muſt bee diſcerned ſpiritually. Therefore with <hi>Hilary</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. 5.</note> we may ſay with hilaritie: <hi>Oh ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mundi ſapientia, Chriſti opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, non ſentiens eſſe Dei virtutem, &amp; mundi ſtultitiam, non intelligens eſſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſapientiam:</hi> oh vnwiſe wiſedome of the worldly wiſe, not vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the opprobrie of the ſon to be the glory of the Father: nor that which is eſteemd folly with men to be the inuincible prudence of God. Then let <hi>rides</hi> be changed to <hi>vides,</hi> then let <hi>vides</hi> be chang'd to <hi>fides,</hi> and faith will refell this preiudicate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, faith will repell this ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous traduction, for faith will tell though <hi>Foras nigra,</hi> yet <hi>intus formo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> though foule without, yet faire within, a faire ſoule, though a foule skinne: the Kings daughter is all<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> glorious within, behold thou art faire my loue, behold thou art faire, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſi pecoris cuſtos, formoſior ipſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20343:11"/>
               <l>Chriſt is the Shepheard, and the Church his Flocke,</l>
               <l>Moſt faire the Shepheard is, and fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Flocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In the Papiſts eies, the ſound Church<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is a buſh, the buſh is ſmal, and of no repute: our Church is vile, and of no eſteeme. Theirs is a Ceder, ours a ſhrub<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theirs a vine, and a pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, ours doth pine, and they repine. They haue antiquity, pleade viſibilitie, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſalitie: wee are a company of few, obſcure, contemptible people, lurking from time to time in ſhades and corners, knowne to few or none. Theirs hath had, and yet hath a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<note place="margin">Farther p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſ. 2. par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey. Dr. <hi>Hill.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>wood</hi> inq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, cap. 14.</note> greater ſway in the world then any other euer had, or hath, how truely ſpoken let <hi>Brerewood</hi> iudge: the Chriſtian part of the world (all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and ſects of that name put together) is as fiue: the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes as ſixe: the Idolaters as nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, beſide that Heatheniſh tract of <hi>Terra incognita,</hi> ſo farre is that from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20343:12"/> truth which this our Iſlands naturall ſonne, bragd in behalfe of his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſpirituall mother.</p>
            <p>But let them bragge: we know who bragges of the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: Antichriſt. I confeſſe indeede<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. 19.</note> the number of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he faithfull, is leſſe far then the number of the faithleſſe: there is more chaffe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n corne in the Lords barne: more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ares then wheat in the Lords field: for one <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> and his family (beeing but eight) the whole world drownd for their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: for one <hi>Lot</hi> and his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold being but foure, all the cities of the plaine burnd for their vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: for one thankefull Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, nine vngratefull leapers: for one<note place="margin">Ier. 3. 14. Reu. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Elias</hi> 450. Pſeudoprophets: but one of a city, and two of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ribe: a few names in <hi>Sardis.</hi> Chriſts ſheepe are not many (<hi>Pauci, pauperes, puſilli,</hi>) for quanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; but more then all the reſt for quality: hee eſteemes more one of his myſticall members, then all the worlds vnhallowed mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: yet is it not Gods family ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20343:12"/> ſmall as to be meaſured by humane Geography: for it is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tyed to the ſeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> as the Iewes would haue it, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yle of Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> as the Donatiſts would haue it, nor to the Sea of Rome, as Popelings would haue it: but God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> all that haue the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and for the tribes of <hi>Iacob</hi> all that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip<note place="margin">Ioh. 4. 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> in ſpirit and truth. Then doe not preoccupate the Lords ſeat, take not vpon thee to iudg thy brethren, neither doe thou deſpaire of thy ſelfe, but leaue iudgement to God, and looke for mercy of the Lord: his foundation is ſure, and hath this ſeale, <hi>Dominus</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>nouit qui ſunt ſui,</hi> the Lord knoweth who are his: and we know that we are his, our Church is his. Though they boaſt of their numbers, deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our handfulls: ſaying, all the world is theirs, ſcarce any corner ours, and who can chooſe but ſuſpect<note place="margin">D<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> a few? we dare, and can ſhare equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them, with our reformed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20343:13"/> Churches oppoſed to them, and if we could not, this rule of theirs will but teach vs to aduance Turciſme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Chriſtianity, and Paganiſme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Mahumetry, the Word aboue the Church, and Hell aboue Heauen: if any proofe can be drawne from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, you know all, the Ceder is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulleſt: if any proofe can bee drawne from multitude, hee that knowes all ſayes, the beſt are feweſt. Thus our Church is a buſh, low in<note place="margin">2 in it own eyes.</note> others eyes, ſo is it a buſh, low in it owne eyes.</p>
            <p>I am duſt and aſhes; I am a worme and no man: <hi>vermis ſum, non v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> I am of no eſtimation, reputation: I am a man of polluted lips: I am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the leaſt of thy mercies; I am not worthy vnder whoſe roofe thou ſhouldſt enter; I am not worthy to vnty the latchet of his ſhooe; I am not worthy to be called thy ſonne; I am not worthy the name of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: humble, lowly, buſhy-confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſifting themſelues to a courſe braine, farre from that humerous, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20343:13"/> Thraſonicall, Phariſaicall, Pyrgopolynice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall Braggadochio.<note place="margin">Aug. hmo. 30 de verb. dom ſecun. Luk.</note> that ſhows not <hi>vulnera,</hi> but <hi>munera,</hi> not his wounds, but his worth; not his miſery, but his brauery. I thanke God, I am not like other men, while<note place="margin">Luk. 18. 11</note> the ſilly buſh, the poore Publican ſtands a farre off, as not daring to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Mount of Gods glory, caſts downe his eyes, as acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging himſelfe guilty, knocks vpon his breſt, the cloſet of his impiety, and with a looke deiected, ſoule perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, voyce ſubmitted, cryes out <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine miſerere mei,</hi> Lord be mercifull to me, to me, I ſay not thy ſonne, I<note place="margin">13</note> haue ſo offended thee; to me, I ſay not thy ſeruant, I haue ſo diſpleaſed thee; to me, I ſay not thy friend, I haue ſo abuſed thee; to me, I ſay not thy creature, I haue ſo rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, but <hi>Domine miſerere mei peccat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris!</hi> Oh Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner: ſo good a follower of the Son of God, is the child of God:<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. <hi>Aug. de te.</hi>
               </note> Learne of me to be meeke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; humble, <hi>Cum humilitatis doctor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20343:14"/> tua:</hi> Pride and peace cannot dwell together, but learne of me to be meeke and humble, and you ſhall<note place="margin">Mat. 11. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> finde reſt to your Soules. Humility is the mother of tranquility: <hi>&amp; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quis humilior, ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to Chriſto ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or:</hi> The more humble thou art, the more like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy Maiſter thou art: but Pride like Colloquintida will imbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a whole pot-full of pottage.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Si tibi ſit copi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aut ſapientia forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur,</l>
               <l>Sola ſuperbia, destr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et omnia, &amp; comitetur.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Though beauty, wealth, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, all thou haſt,</p>
            <p>Pride will them all demolliſh quite at laſt.</p>
            <p>Oh be not ignorant of what thou art, <hi>Dumus, Rubus,</hi> a Buſh, a Shrub, <hi>nequam, nequicquam,</hi> nought, nor ought: Thy Body is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as much to ſay, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thy Soules Sepulcher. Thy Soule is <hi>anima,</hi> as much to ſay as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a winde that paſſeth ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that paſſeth the winde in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20343:14"/> vanity: Thou waſt <hi>Corpus,</hi> a Body, but <hi>Cor</hi> is gone, thy heart loſt, onely<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>pus</hi> remaines putrifaction, ſo vaine a thing is man: Then <hi>esto quodes,</hi> bee what thou art: Thou art low, bee lowly: As holineſſe, ſo lowlineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Saints.</p>
            <p>Thus for ſtature, now for nature:<note place="margin">2. Nature.</note> Our Church is a Buſh. Naturally and for the moſt part to a Buſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs theſe parts, <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Ramus. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex, folia, fructus.</hi> A Buſh hath natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a Roote: ſecondly a Body: thirdly Barke: fourthly Branches: fiftly Leaues: ſixtly and fruit, ſo hath<note place="margin">Scaliger de Subtil. ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 40. P. 2.</note> the Church, onely heer's the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, they haue their branches vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, wee our branches (legges and armes) downwards: wee inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a skinne, they in a barke; they haue their mouth in the earth, wee ours towards Heauen, &amp;c. Chriſt is the Root, the Root of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> the Root<note place="margin">Roote, Rom. 15. 12. Eſa. 11. 1. Reu. 5. 5. Eſa. 53. 2. Eſa. 11. 10.</note> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> called a Root in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: a Root in his Paſſion: a Root in his Aſcention: a Root in the generall Iudgments diſcuſſion. Now
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20343:15"/> is the Axe layd to the roote of the<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> tree: thou bear'ſt not the root but the roote thee: As the roote is to the Buſh, ſo is Chriſt to the Church.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Fundamentum. Being a prop &amp; ſtay to vphold it.</item>
               <item>2. Alimentum. Bringing of ſap &amp; iuyee to nouriſh it.<note place="margin">1 Founda.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>No other foundation can any man lay than Ieſus Chriſt, which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy layd: angular ſtone, immoueable rock, elect, &amp; precious: There is none other named in heauen or earth, by whom to bee ſaued: though ſome think that Philoſophers may be ſaued without him. But other rootes hath<note place="margin">Rome.</note> 
               <hi>Rome;</hi> thus they ſay: thus they pray, <hi>Papa Domine mei miſerere;</hi> O Lord Pope in thee is my hope, haue mercy vpon mee: and <hi>qui tollis peccata mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di miſerere noſtri;</hi> as the <hi>Sicilians</hi> to Pope <hi>Martin the</hi> 4: thou that takeſt<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serres</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentory.</note> away the ſins of the world haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs. To the Virgin:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh foelix Puerpera,</l>
               <l>Noſtrapians ſcelera;</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20343:15"/>
               <l>Iure matris impera<note place="margin">Dr. Hall.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Redemptori:</l>
               <l>Oh happy mother of that ſonne</l>
               <l>That hath all our ſinnes fordonne;</l>
               <l>By a mothers right wee pray thee,</l>
               <l>Bid our Redeemer to obey thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Further:<note place="margin">Guili. Nen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigenſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l. 2. cap. 16</note>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Tuper Thomae ſanguinem, quem pro Chriſto fudit;</l>
               <l>Fac vt ego aſcenderem vbi Chriſtus ſedit:</l>
               <l>By the blood of St. Thomas which was ſhed on the ground;</l>
               <l>Let me aſcend thither where Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ſits crownd. <hi>And,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aqua benedicta,</l>
               <l>Dele delicta:</l>
               <l>By this water bleſt,</l>
               <l>Bee thy ſinnes releaſt; bee it life &amp; health vnto thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Remiſſion cold</l>
               <l>Nere knowne of old.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>The Guilt of ſin put from thee:</hi> &amp; infinite other: Rotren rootes, Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20343:16"/> reedes, waterleſſe welles: of noe life, force, ſtrength. <hi>Sunt infirma quaedam refugia, ad quae cum quis fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerit</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. 45.</note> 
               <hi>magis infirmatur, quam confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur:</hi> they that truſt to them are not onely deceaud in them, but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them. But Chriſt is the roote of our ſaluation.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Pendimus a te</l>
               <l>Tendimus ad te</l>
               <l>Credimus in te:</l>
               <l>non niſi per te op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time<note place="margin">Boyſ.</note> domine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wee depend on thee,</l>
               <l>Wee belong to thee,</l>
               <l>Wee beleeue in thee:</l>
               <l>Lets bee ſaud by thee,</l>
               <l>oh ſweete Ieſu.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Other Rootes hath the Carnall<note place="margin">Carnal.</note> men, &amp; women; taking, making; ſtaues, and ſtaies; broken ſtaues, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtayes: meere Quagmires to themſelues. As the Courtier that builds his houſes on the fauour of<note place="margin">1. Courtier</note> Princes, whoſe breath is, (and ſhalbe ſhortly) in their noſthrils: Truſt them not, <hi>non eſt Salus in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> their is no health in them, no help in them: the Salue of their tongue like the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liua
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20343:16"/> thereof hath ſome venome in it.<note place="margin">Pſa. 146. Pſa. 82. 6</note> 
               <hi>Dixi Dii,</hi> I haue ſayd you are Gods; but you ſhall all die, &amp; die like men: for what are they, but as thou thy thy ſelfe? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſoule and ſoyle, the one nothing but a puffe of wind; the other nothing but a pile of duſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> Eſa. 2. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gen. 2. 7.</note> both ſhall paſſe away, euen as the wind ſcatters the duſt. And who would truſt duſt? it wil ſlip out of thy hand and deceaue thee; &amp; more than ſo flie in thine eies and blind thee: <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri magni ſunt montes naufragoſi, quo Nauem quiſque cum impulerit ſolui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. Tract.</note> mightie men are mightie rocks, thy ship ſplits if thou launch towards them. The <hi>Lawyer:</hi> the root of whoſe tree is a mercenary Fee. Woe bee<note place="margin">2 Lawyer.</note> vnto you Scribes and Lawyers Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures, Offices, Sutes, and Pleaes, Wars &amp; Iarres; procure your eaſe: and how could you feed ſo fat without them? But, <hi>Nouerint vniuerſi per preſentes:</hi> bee it known vnto all men by theſe preſents, that ſuch ſiluer-Cauſidiciſts money-Spermologiſts, ſhall once plead hard at the barr of Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20343:17"/> &amp; ſhall not be hard: their Caſe ſhall bee ill like a Chancery-bill, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully complaining, not mercy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning, whilſt Bribery is raigning.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vſurer:</hi> who growes on a<note place="margin">3 Vſurer.</note> Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke; his mind is on his Mine, thats his Roote, &amp; there hee rootes. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">* loue of money. 1. Tim. 6. 10</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Philargury is the roote of villany: Couetuouſnes, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntaine of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. He ſels the ayre, takes mony for time, contracts with Satan, giues his ſoul for ſurety, when hee puts out his mony, puts his hand to the bill, when he receaues the vſe. But the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Obligacion is ſuch, that if<note place="margin">Luk. 19. 8.</note> hee doe not <hi>Zacchize</hi> (reſtore) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently (and heele bee hangd firſt) he, &amp; his heires ſhal bee quite extinct.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>De male quaeſitis non gaudet tertius haeres.</l>
               <l>Three heires ſucceſſiuely doe ſcarce inioy,</l>
               <l>Ill wealth ſucceſſiuely without an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy.<note place="margin">Miniſter.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The <hi>Miniſter:</hi> whoſe Roote is in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20343:17"/> the Chancel not the Church: Tythes and glebes, commendams and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications; are that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e growes vpon: <hi>Hara domeſtica,</hi> his owne Stie; not <hi>Arae Dominica,</hi> Gods houſe: not caring to, 1 <hi>Feed 2 feed 3 feed;</hi> either by his 1 teaching, 2 liuing, 3 relei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: but Carking wholly to feed himſelfe, ſhall I ſay wjth <hi>Ezechiell</hi> with a Barley-loafe? noe, with the <hi>Panada</hi> of fineſt Manchet, while the Temple of god remaines vnbuilt. O Prophet couet not profit; tis time, if euer, now to awake leaſt like <hi>Ionas</hi> his Gourde, thy meanes ſlake, and<note place="margin">Ionah 4. 7.</note> thy Superintendency another take.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epicure, de grege porcus.</hi> That is a<note place="margin">4 Epicure.</note> louer of pleaſure more than of God therefore pleaſure, not god is his root,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> he grows in the Celler vnder the tap, or elſe in ſome corner in a wantons lap: either carouſing the three <hi>Outs;</hi> 1 wit out of the pate, 2 drinke out of the pot, 3 coyne out of the purſe: or hazarding all at the three Innes, 1 ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie in Bedlam, chaſtitie in a Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-houſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20343:18"/> 3 reuenues in the compter. Are not moſt of our <hi>Deſpots</hi> turnd <hi>Toſpots?</hi> muſicke for the eare: beautie for the eie: Pomanders for the noſe: Banquets for the tooth: healths for the throte: (noe health for the body) Hell for the Soul. But
<q>
                  <l>Oh bone Ieſu, fons indificiens,</l>
                  <l>Tu humana corda reficiens;</l>
                  <l>Ad te curro te ſolum ſitiens,</l>
                  <l>Tu mihi domine ſolus ſuffici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns:</l>
                  <l>Oh ſweete ſauiour thou art our ſtay</l>
                  <l>When theſe mundane props ſhall vaniſh away,</l>
                  <l>Thou art that Roote that ſhall neuer decay.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the fundament; ſo he<note place="margin">2 Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> giues aliment, iuyce, and nutriment, moyſture and nouriſhment to the Buſh, his Church. <hi>Radix eſt os <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſtomachus arboris;</hi> the roote is the mouth and ſtomacke of the tree: mouth to feed it, ſtomach to nouriſh it: giues ſuſtentation, which breedes vegetation, and fructification; nor would it haue verdure, or greeniſh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20343:18"/> tincture, without this ſappie moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure; but would bee leaueles, liueles, &amp; fruitles. Euen ſo <hi>Chriſtus eſt os et ſtomachus fidelis;</hi> Chriſt is the mouth and ſtomach of his Church; mouth for inſtruction, ſtomach for refection: <hi>manna</hi> of the ſoul to feed mans ſoul: bread of life to breed mans life, ſowen in heauen; reapt in earth; in'd by <hi>Mary;</hi> threſht by the Phariſies; ground on the croſſe, betweene two ſtones, beetweene two theeues; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the Sepulcher; diſtributed, in the Sacrament, where god doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to euery faithful branch its part: <hi>Sumit vnus ſumunt mille, quantum iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti tantum ille:</hi> whoeuer feedes on this refection, eates and drinkes his owne<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> ſaluation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my fleſh is meat, my blood is drink; fleſh and blood, meate and drink; meate indeed, drinke indeed:<note place="margin">Pſa.</note> therefore as the Hart thirſteth for the riuers of water; ſo doth my hart thirſt for this heauenly moyſture.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Cuius guttulis abluuntur animae</l>
               <l>Cuius riuulis diſpelluntur maculae</l>
               <l>Quem qui effugiunt moriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur viui</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20343:19"/>
               <l>Quem qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tur viu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi:</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Buſh hath a bole, trunke, or<note place="margin">2 Bodie. Rom. 12. Eph. 4. 4.</note> body; ſo hath the Church: we are many members, yet but one body glued, and ſerued, and cemented to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; with the morter of Vnitie plaſter of Amitie, aſphaltum of Vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie; where the King is the head, Councell the eies, Iudges the eares, Lawes the teeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Paſtours the toung<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> good Houſkeepers the ſtomache, Huſbandmen the feet, Souldiors the hands; the Pope was the haire, the haire of the head aboue the crowne; till <hi>Harry</hi> the eight did ſhaue him downe. <hi>God grant his trentals ſtill to bee excrements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are all baptized into one body.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> Why doth then the Guelph &amp; Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belin, why doth the red and whitroſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faction, or Papiſt, Hugonet, or Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian, harrow and til the ſoyl of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Vnum corpus, vnus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mus;</hi> one Bole, one Soul: but of this ſuccinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3 Barke.</note> cauſe by others ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>The Buſh hath a Barke, ſo the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20343:19"/> Church.</p>
            <p>The Bark to the Buſh is a beauty or ornament: 2 a couer or tegument: A good conuerſation is ſuch to the chriſtian: this doth <hi>Corpus tegere, Cor protegere;</hi> deck the ſoul, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the body &amp; moues god to reſpect both. A fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re Rinde argues a good mind; good Conuerſation a ſigne of ſanctification; as virtuous manners are precious treaſures, commodious to vs and alſo to others, to vs <hi>ad iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficandum</hi> though not effectiuely: ſo we are iuſtified by Chriſt, not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſiuely, ſo wee are iuſtified by faith yet declaratiuely by iuſt and holy virtuous workes. So our Sauiour of himſelfe, <hi>the workes that I haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> beare witneſſe what I am:</hi> to others <hi>ad aedificandum</hi> that others ſeeing our workes on earth, may glorifie our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heuen. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tur exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis,</hi> man is led by practice, more than inſtruction, like pliable wax for any<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neca E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. lib. 1 Epiſt. 1.</note> impreſſion. But if you bee either <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le agentes</hi> doing wickedly, or <hi>nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes</hi> lying idly, or <hi>aliud agentes</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſeemingly,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20343:20"/> your Couer is gone, your honour's none, you are barkles Buſhes, naked Forreſters. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Buſh hath not onely a barke without, but alſo a little Filme with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: ſo haue god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Darlings, as faire outward parts, ſo good inward hearts, corporall vrbanity, and cordiall ſinceritie, as knowing that, <hi>Sermo interpres cordis apud v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum, cor interpres ſermonis apud Deum;</hi> men iudge of our harts by<note place="margin">Philo-Iud.</note> the outward countenance, but god of our works by the inward conſcience: therefore as they hang out a buſh, ſo they haue alſo Wine, lodginge for Chriſt as well as a ſigne.</p>
            <p>As pargetted walles, ſo garniſhed chambers, &amp; furniſhed cloſets, ſwept &amp; waſht, rubd and pared from duſt, cobwebs, filth and rubbiſh; <hi>ab offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioribus</hi> ſmaler offences, and <hi>ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioribus</hi> ſweeter concupiſcences, <hi>&amp; grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oribus</hi> groſſer vices: know you not that you are temples of the Holy Ghoſt? but the holy-ghoſt will not dwell in thoſe temples, where En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20343:20"/> ſtands at the doore, Wrath leanes in the porch, drunkennes lyes on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ore, Gluttony ſits at the table, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery keepes the bed, &amp; Pride lookes out at the window.</p>
            <p>Let vs now with <hi>Zacche</hi> get vp to<note place="margin">4 Branches.</note> the branches, that we may eie &amp; eſpie our beloued Ieſus. The buſh hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of twigges, redundance of ſprigges, ſprouts, &amp; ſhuts, boughes, and armes: ſo hath our ſlender tender Church: whereof ſome are tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſome ſpirituall: the iſſue of the wombe, the iſſue of the word: nor without the former can wee haue the later: for no <hi>filij ſoeculi,</hi> no <hi>filij coeli,</hi> no generation, no regeneration: barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was a curſe among the Iewes, wee thinke it a croſſe among vs Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. Children are the firſt, the beſt bleſſing. Thus could<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Iuno</hi> preach to <hi>Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Sunt mihi bis ſeptempreſtanti cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nimphae:</l>
               <l>Quarum, quae forma pulcherrima, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</l>
               <l>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bio iungam ſtabili, propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amque
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20343:21"/> dicabo.</l>
               <l>(Aeole) qua faciet pulchra te pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le beatum.</l>
               <l>Twice ſeauen beautious nimphes I haue in ſtore,</l>
               <l>Whereof the faireſt I will giue to thee:</l>
               <l>Inſtable wedlock which ſhall bleſſe thee more</l>
               <l>With children, than great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue hath bleſſed mee,<note place="margin">Pſa. 128.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>And thus ſhall the man be bleſſed that feareth the Lord. <hi>His wife ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee like a fruitfull vine by the houſe ſides: his children like Oliue branches round about his table: vt Angeli in circuitu throni dei,</hi> like a garland of angels round about gods throne: <hi>vt ſtellae in circuitu Poli Arctici,</hi> as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of ſtars round about the North-Pole. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> asked <hi>Socrates</hi> how hee could indure the chiding of his wife; <hi>Socrates</hi> ask'd <hi>Alcibiades</hi> how hee could indure the cackling of his hens, ſayes the one <hi>pariunt pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> my hens hatch me chickens; but the other <hi>parit filios,</hi> my wife beares<note place="margin">Pſal.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20343:21"/> me children. Happy he that hath his<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> quiuer full of them, he ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſpeake with his enemie in the gate: they preſerue our <hi>Species,</hi> and after a ſort make vs immortall, by deriuing life from the roote to the branches, from the Father to the Son, from the Sonne to the ſonnes ſonne in <hi>longinquum,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes for many generations. But becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe are not milde but wild, not fertile but ſtertile, not ſtreight, but crooked branches, ſome like <hi>Cain</hi> butchering their brothers, ſome like <hi>Nero,</hi> murthering their mothers, ſome like <hi>Ammon</hi> defiling their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and others like <hi>Ham,</hi> reuiling their Fathers, let vs caſt our eyes <hi>a ventre ad verbum,</hi> from the iſſue of the wombe to the iſſue of the word. As many as are begotten by the word of God, are branches of the buſh, members of the Church of God. God husbandeth, the Sacrament wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth, the Spirit refreſheth, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance moyſteneth, the miniſter plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the word ſeedeth, and feedeth,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20343:22"/> and breedeth, then the Branch ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15 35.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O powerful Sperm able to make <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> quake, the iaylor ſhake, of ſtony harts to rayſe vp children to <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; metamorphize the moſt obdurate: Lyons into lambs, beares into kids, the couetous, as mercifull as <hi>Iob,</hi> and liberall as <hi>Zache:</hi> the timerous, as bold as <hi>Laurence,</hi> and couragious as the Martyrs: the luxurious, as chaſt as <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and continent as <hi>Iudeth,</hi> the blood-thirſty as tender-hearted as <hi>Zippora,</hi> and deteſting blood as <hi>Iacob:</hi> finally, the vicious as penitent as <hi>Peter,</hi> and louing Chriſt as <hi>Mary: modo pateant aures, &amp; ſitiant ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam pectus:</hi> Theſe are the branches of the true vine, (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.) King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibeiba</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lanct. lib. 3. inſt. 26. Pet Mart. Dec. lib. 3.</note> had his pallace in a tree: I am ſure <hi>Iehoua</hi> dwells in theſe Branches: for though the world be his conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Scripture his dying room, yet is euer the ſoule of the righteous<note place="margin">Heb. 3. 6. Pſal. 132.</note> his Bedde-chamber. Wee are his houſe.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20343:22"/>
               <l>Where he ſets his reſt,</l>
               <l>And builds his neſt,</l>
               <l>And thinkes it beſt, to tarry</l>
               <l>If we to ſinne</l>
               <l>Our ſoule within</l>
               <l>Doe not begin to marry.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But why doe I throſtle ſo long in theſe branches? I muſt leaue them<note place="margin">Leaues.</note> and come to the leaues. The Buſh hath them, the Church doth not want them. The leaues are part of that bleſſing which God doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, to ſuch as are beſt, to ſuch as are bleſt: He ſhall bee like a Iuniper, a Buſh, a Palme, a Date, a tree, Date<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> Palm-tree, planted by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſide: (his regeneration) which ſhall bring forth fruite in due ſeaſon (his ſanctification) whoſe leaues ſhall not fall (his continuation) he begins<note place="margin">Trem. in Pſal. 1.</note> well, goes on well, ends well, ſo all is well, <hi>Quid per folium niſi fidem &amp; amorem?</hi> What other are theſe, not falling leaues, not falſing leaues, not fayling leaues, not fainting leaues, but faith and loue? Faith and loue are the louely leaues of this liuely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20343:23"/> Buſh. Faith in the great little Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe<note place="margin">Fayth.</note> of the ſoule (though loue be the Chancelour, memory the Regiſter, conſcience the Paritour, prayſe the Choriſtour) is the Arch-biſhop, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan, ſuperintendent of all other graces. <hi>Fides eſt prima quae ſubiugat animam deo.</hi> Faith is that which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>animam deo.</hi> Faith is that which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt, or beſt) tyes the ſoule firſt, and faſt, to the firſt, and laſt, <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>Vne</hi> and <hi>Trine, Trine</hi> and <hi>Vne</hi> bleſſed God. Loue is the kernell in the Nut, the pearle in the Oyſter, Dyamond in the ring, luſter of the Sunne, chaſt <hi>Diana</hi> among her maydes: humility is her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayde, charity her kitchin-mayde, chaſtity her chamber-mayde, and gracious ſobrietie a mayd of honour. Oh you veſtall nymphes; let not hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe wooe you, nor couetouſneſſe winne you, nor concupiſcence wed you, nor ſurfetting beuomit you: Be wiſe virgins that your lampe may be loue, and oyle faith. If you haue faith, you cannot want loue, for one of theſe leaues buds from the other,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20343:23"/> loue from faith, righteouſneſſe from holineſſe. Faith is fire; fire is opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: where there is fire, there will be heat, the greater fire, the greater heat, the leſſer fire, the leſſer heat: no fire, no heat, no heat, no fire: <hi>Fides</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luther.</hi> Gal 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>debet pingueſcere operibus:</hi> Our fayth muſt worke by loue: if wee haue no loue, our fire is extinct, our candle<note place="margin">Ientile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> out. Let it neuer bee ſayd of vs (as one ſometime of the Monkes of his time that their faſts were fat, and ptayers leane) our faith hot, our loue cold. Oh ſhame that the child of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhould reſemble hell: Hell hath fire, (<hi>Qui non credent, ſentient</hi>) but that fire hath no light.</p>
            <p>I doubt wee haue too many ſuch fire-brands of hell, that haue a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing fire of faith in their toung, but the fire of their faith, makes not their loue boyle, their light doth not ſhine out before men, leaueleſſe trees, emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty clouds, waterleſſe wells (like the<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 16.</note> ſumptuous Sumpter-mules of that vaine-glorious Cardinall) ſeeming without wondrous rich, but nothing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20343:24"/> within ſaue old ſhooes and bootes, ſtones and rubbiſh. Gods child is Gods Prieſt, therefore muſt beare on his breaſt not onely <hi>Vrim</hi> (Science) but <hi>Thummim</hi> too (conſcience), cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thoſe that like <hi>Adonibezecke</hi> want theſe thumbs: and in his skirts, not onely Bells (a ſounding profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) but Pomegranates too (a ſound deuotion) faith muſt haue a nature, as well as a name, otherwiſe it is <hi>fides nuda, fides nulla,</hi> a bare faith, a no faith, and wants leaues to couer it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Once more! theſe leaues are phyſicall of condition: greene of complexion.</p>
            <p>Phiſical leaues: the leaues ſhal be for<note place="margin">Phyſicall. Ezech. 47. 12, 13. Reu. 2. 22.</note> medcine: the leaues ſhall bee for the healing of nations: Faith, and loue the leaues of our Buſh, heale, and helpe, cure, and recouer the <hi>Vertigo</hi> of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, hecticke of laſciuiouſnes, lethergie of idleneſſe, wolfe of vſury, conſumption of enuy, quotidian of blaſphemie, with other the like ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſeaſes. Doe but plucke theſe leaues with the hand of deuotion,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20343:24"/> mixe them with the Syrrup of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bruiſe them in the morter of a good conſcience, and boyle them on the fire of true repentance, apply them to thy ſoule both ful and faſting, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, noone, and euening, and thou ſhalt ſee a miracle; a dead man reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to life. Greene leaues: her leaues<note place="margin">Greene. le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17. 8. Pſal. 1. 5.</note> ſhall be green both ſummer and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (<hi>i. e.</hi>) in the tempe of proſperitie, and tempeſt of aduerſitie: alwayes greene, the leaues ſhall not wither, the froſt ſhall not nip them, nor the ayre blaſt them, nor the wind ſcatter them: Faith and loue on the altar of<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 24.</note> the heart, are like fire on the altar, not to goe out, or depart like the ſtone in <hi>Plinie,</hi> which being once made not, could neuer be cold.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe indeed, they may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time bee ſeene in the Orient in their full heat, &amp; feruor, ſomtime in the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident in the declining of their luſter, but men, Angels, diuells, can neuer extinguiſh them: for hee that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth is paſſed already from death to life: and he that loueth, neuer faileth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 8.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20343:25"/> or falleth from God, but is ſo hotte, much water cannot quench it, <hi>Nec immergent nubes,</hi> neither can the<note place="margin">Cant. 8. 7.</note> cloudes drowne it. The Cardinall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: that a man may make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke<note place="margin">Bel. de iuſt. lib. 3. 14.</note> both of faith and loue, but I haue neither faith to beleeue him, nor loue to like him, nor enuy him his red hat with this label, this bable: for whom God loueth, hee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer loueth; neither can any one ſnatch them out of the hand of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>He that is elect, and whoſe faith worketh by loue, eyther neuer fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,<note place="margin">Aug. de Cor &amp; Gra. c. 8.</note> or if he fall, is rayſed and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued before this life be ended.</p>
            <p>If your leaues be true, they can neuer wither, if wither away, they were neuer true: then let your faith, and loue haue a continuall ſpring, that you may bud now, and flouriſh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes: bee not Gods prentiſes a while, and the diuels iourney-men after, God will ſcorne the blew bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, if Satan ſup the creame. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not <hi>Epheſus,</hi> remember you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20343:25"/> not your firſt faith, firſt loue: hold on, hold out, <hi>Vſque ad extremum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae terminum,</hi> to the December of your dayes, till your ſpirits aſcend to heauen, to him that gaue them, your bodies deſcend to the earth whereof he made them, your carkaſſes tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend on foure mens ſhoulders to <hi>Golgotha</hi> the place of dead-mens skulls.</p>
            <p>Thus, and this for the Root, Body,<note place="margin">Fruites.</note> Barke, Branch, and leaues: while I ſhake the fruites, prepare the basket of attention to gather them: the mouth of meditation to chew them: and the ſtomacke of obedience to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them. The myrtle is a little buſh,<note place="margin">In Elide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> but it hath many berries: <hi>Pauſanius</hi> makes it an Embleme of one of the graces. The Church is this myrtle, fruitfull, and fertile, and like <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus</hi> his tree, euery child of God is fructiferous: he is that true tree of<note place="margin">Reu. 22. 2.</note> life which bare twelue manner of fruits, and yeelds her fruite euery moneth: Theſe twelue fruites are twelue good workes, ſixe for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20343:26"/> and ſixe for the ſoule: you may wedde them together in that old<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſtich.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Viſito, poto, cibo, recoligo, veſtio, condo.</l>
               <l>Inſtrue, caſtiga, remitte, ſolare, fer, ora.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To viſite the ſicke, is a wholeſome<note place="margin">1. Viſito.</note> fruite, <hi>Religio munda non mundi:</hi> it is pure religion and vndefiled to viſite<note place="margin">Iam. 1. vlt.</note> the fatherleſſe and widdowes in their affliction. Bee not ſlow to viſite the<note place="margin">Eccl. 7. 35.</note> ſicke, for this ſhall make thee belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Chriſt takes this office as done to himſelfe, <hi>When I was ſicke, and in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
               <hi>priſon ye viſited me:</hi> therefore let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one viſit: The King his Subiects, the realme is ſicke, almoſt ſicke to death: from the ſhoulders to the ſole, many infirmities.</p>
            <p>1. The ſhoulders (the Nobles) in many places are ſicke of phlegmons, and tumours: either attending in Court (but what ſayes the Prouerbe? <hi>Exeat Aula qui vult eſſe pius</hi>) or ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling in citty, while their Emiſſaries (<hi>Bayliues</hi>) are rifling the Countrey:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20343:26"/> viſiting not the whole, the ſicke, but the ſicke the whole to make them ſicke.</p>
            <p>There was once but one racke, and that in the Towre for Traytors, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcelions, and malefactors: now wee haue in euery hamlet too many for honeſt Tenants, huſbandmen, and farmers: enhaunſing their <hi>fines finem facere,</hi> to vndoe them, improouing their rents, to rent their eſtates, and impoueriſh them, or incloſing their Commons, that their <hi>Oues &amp; Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, &amp; caetera peccora campi,</hi> cannot peepe out of doores for feare of a treſpaſſe, ſo hedging God out, and fencing the diuell in (here a buſh, and there a thiefe) that God might iuſtly ſend ſome hunting <hi>Nimrod</hi> to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple downe their quickſets. The feet (the Commonaltie) are ſore pained with botches, and vlcers, as Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers that eate vp Gods people, as if they were bread: Foreſtallers, that ſcarce ſuffer Gods people to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bread, vnleſſe they will buy it at their price, or can doe as the diuell
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20343:27"/> counceld Chriſt, turne ſtones into bread: Scriueners that hale men to the Counter with parchment halters: Brokers that deale with old garments as the moſt with voyd offices. Who will giue moſt? without a pawne, a man ſhall ſooner borrow their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, then their money: Breakers that gallop they care not in whoſe debt, then play at moſt in hiddles till they trot out on the backe of a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or skip vp into the ſaddle of a reference: while the poore of the land are bridled, and ſadled, and rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and ſpurred, expecting the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power to viſit them.</p>
            <p>The Iudge his Circuit: Iuſtice (like<note place="margin">2</note> that traueller twixt Iericho and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem) is falne amongſt theeues. Couetouſneſſe that old theefe hath put out her eyes, mercenary Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers haue deflowred her, Bribery hath cut out her tong, countenance in Court hath deaft her, Partialitie hath robd her of her ſword, willfull conniuence hath broken her ballance, and a ſwarme of perfidious bayliues
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20343:27"/> are ready to cut her throat: helpe ſage Senators, and viſit this deſolate widow, doe right, be expedite while<note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 3.</note> you haue light: be not <hi>Iudices, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ius dicentes,</hi> nor <hi>legis-latores quaſi legis latrones,</hi> but doers, rather then ſpeakers, treaders, rather then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the law.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould great theeues hang vp little ones? or <hi>Saul</hi> ſpare <hi>Agag</hi> for pretexts? or <hi>Vliſſes</hi> ſwarue from <hi>Telemachus</hi> in the furrow? take heed, perhaps ſome ſeuere <hi>Cambyſes</hi> ſhall make cuſhions of your skinnes for your ſucceſſors: Let not poore ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyants both pay, and pray, and ſtay, and in the end goe empty away. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vniuſt Demurr anagramati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed is murder.</p>
            <p>The Bp. his Dioceſſe: the plague<note place="margin">3</note> of Egypt is lightamongſt vs; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, too many are ſicke of the ſcab. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion though not deceaſed is ſore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed, while truth keepes her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with a ſcratched face.</p>
            <p>Atheiſts would ſtifle her: while walking <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>-like vpon
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20343:28"/> the turrets of nature, and battlements of reaſon, they breath forth blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie againſt God, and infamy againſt man: is not this great <hi>Babel,</hi> which I haue built? Is not that which wee<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 4. 27.</note> doe, done by natures power? haue not we wit? haue not we will? haue not wee reaſon? haue not we skill? thinking to be good, when indeede they are ill: diſarming themſelues while they make fleſh their arme, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting, neglecting the power of God: but when his name is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Adder-like, they clap one eare to the ground, while with their tayle they ſtop the other: wolfe-like they barke againſt the reſplendent moone: Owle-like they fly the light at noon: Aſſe-like they bray againſt the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Viper-like gnaw out the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of their mother, ſaying with the<note place="margin">Pſal. 14. 1.</note> foole there is no God: yet ſcience in the moſt, conſcience in the reſt, notions in the ſoule, motions of the heauens, ptoclaime to his face that his toung is a lyer.</p>
            <p>Papiſts would ſmoother her: loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20343:28"/> the Church with ſuch a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of traditions, that groaning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen, ſhee is fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e into ſweat.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> excommunicated one <hi>Virgill</hi> a Biſhop for confeſſing the Antipodes: and Popery would exterminate our Virgin truth for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing their ceremonies (the want whereof is the beſt company: <hi>cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia a care<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do</hi>) O Lord ſend this curſt cow but ſhort hornes, elſe truth had need to looke to her eſſence, for ſhee will bee in danger to looſe her exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence. If Father <hi>Sweet</hi> be her Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, he will teach her ſpeake Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, while the purchaſe of Chriſt ſhall bee fed with a halfe Sacrament, a wafer-cake, and now and then, a draught of the whores holy-water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottle: Tranſubſtantiation of the bread, iuſtification by workes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of Saints, adoration of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, peregrinations to <hi>Loretto,</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall decrees, Remiſh gloſſes, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh aſſes, knauiſh Seminaries, and a myriad of other their Babyloniſh
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20343:29"/> opinions.</p>
            <p>Seperatiſts would ſtrangle her, whilſt with the ſheeres of ſhameleſſe diſſention, they ſo cut and diuide the coat of Chriſt Ieſus, that <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon</hi> may iuſtly laugh at vs; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring as much on the right hand, as Antichriſts diſciples on the left: for whereas they would ouerpreſſe vs with too many, theſe will not admit vs any ceremonies, but like the naked Adamites would haue a bare Church without the apparrell of all order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the tenth of Spayne, ſayd blaſphemouſly, <hi>Si in principio mundi ipſe deo adfuiſſet, multa melius, ordinatiuſque condenda fuiſſe,</hi> that if<note place="margin">Lipſig.</note> God in the beginning had choſen him for a Councellour, many things ſhould haue been ordered better, and with leſſe confuſion; and if theſe men had as much power in their hands, as ſlander in their tongues, and faction in their breaſts, many things in our Church gouernment ſhould bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then they are, for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Quod vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus ſanctum eſt,</hi> is as truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20343:29"/> by them, as it was by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts: Biſhops? Downe with them, down with them euen to the ground, beſt let euery priuate miniſter bee a ſuperintendent: the ſurplice as the whores ſmocke torne in pieces: the ring put in the beares ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out: and for the cap, what ſhould they doe with any, but a cap of maintenance: ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted prayers (ſaith one of them) are ſtinking prayers: and God (ſaith an other) is like a man that loues pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage<note place="margin">Pow. Brow.</note> well, but as man may bee glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with one broath often vſed, ſo will God with one prayer often ſaid: yet theſe are the men, that make the ſilly Plebeians beleeue they know more (like <hi>Marcian</hi> and <hi>Montanus</hi>) then euer Chriſt or his Apoſtles; when like the <hi>Lesbian</hi> Maſons, they rather frame the ſquare of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their braine-ſicke poſitions, then bow their poſitions to the not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Scriptures. Therefore it is no wonder, if in ſtead of the trees daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, the dogges fall a barking, while ſuch vnskilfull <hi>Neanth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> handle <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20343:30"/> his harpe. Helpe ſoueraigne iudge. Bp. viſite theſe diſtreſſed, oppreſſed may dens, charity, iuſtice, truth, elſe God will viſite for theſe things. But who am I that <hi>Phormi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>-like I ſhould preſume to read any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Chiualry to <hi>Hannibal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let each man viſit his neighbour, brother, ſiſter, friend, enimy, in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and in priſon, in diſtreſſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery: The day-ſtarre from on high hath viſited vs, and wee muſt viſite one another: not as <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth did his father to ſnatch away his crowne, nor as many amongſt vs to catch at the ſicke mans crownes (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring one Teſtament of a rich man, before both the Teſtaments of God) but as the virgin (bleſſed for euer) did viſit hercozen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſhe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Chriſt in her wombe, wee muſt carry Chriſt, as in our hearts, ſo in our tongues to miniſter (as what worldly thing ſoeuer is wanting) ſo ſome words of comfort to diſeaſed Patients, that their hearts like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> may leape and ſpring within
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20343:30"/> them.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis pure religion vndefilde,</l>
               <l>To viſit Gods diſtreſſed child.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To quench the thirſty is a moyſt<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poto.</hi> 2. Pſal.</note> fruite: the thirſty ground cries for water, the thirſty ſtomacke cals for moyſture: God giues the one, giue<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> we the other. Tis the Apoſtles man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, if thy enemy thirſt giue him drinke (how much more thy friend?) he that requires it will one day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite it: thus ſayth the Lord, he that giues not a gallon, but a cruſe, not a pottle, but a pot, not a but, but a cup, but a ſup, not of Nectar, but of water, be it cold water, to a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, <hi>Non perdet mercedem,</hi> ſhall not looſe his reward. But leaſt I looſe my ſelfe in this but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or teach you to wring at a wrong ſpigget, learn in briefe whoſe thirſt to quench. Who is drier then the drunkard? Tis the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ap-houſe catch; Drinke will make a man drunke, and drunke will make a man dry: <hi>Quo plus ſunt pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, plus ſitiuntur aquae,</hi> the more drinke they haue, the more drinke they craue: though with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20343:31"/> 
               <hi>Maximine</hi> they drinke an Amphora a day (almoſt ſixe gallons) yet by no<note place="margin">Iul. capit. Herod.</note> meanes they will leaue their reckning pot, but euer they cry one tooth is dry. Shall we quench this thirſt? No, vnleſſe we will quench it in them, as the Indians did in the Spaniards: they with boyling gold (eate gold Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oliu. de Noort. Benz. lib. 1. cap.</hi> 23. Luk. 16. 25.</note> ſcalding broth were too coole for theſe hot throats.</p>
            <p>Be as inexorable to them, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was to <hi>Diues,</hi> and wet not<note place="margin">1.</note> the tippe of thy finger to coole their<note place="margin">2.</note> tong, much leſſe to augment or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke<note place="margin">3.</note> their thirſt, leaſt of all to make thy ſelfe merry. Woe vnto him that giues his neighbour drinke, that puts his bottle vnto him, and makes him drunk, he may drinke too, but ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<note place="margin">Abbacu. 2. 15, 16.</note> ſpewing ſhall bee on his glory: But broach thy beere to ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digence inforceth to aske. <hi>Dapotum ouibus,</hi> water theſe ſheepe, bee it at<note place="margin">Gen. 29 7.</note> the well-head, and at the bleating of ſuch cattle let the rock of your heart guſh out ſtreames of pitty.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:20343:31"/>
               <l>Let not your foſſet once be dry</l>
               <l>To ſuch as want compells to cry.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To feede the hungry is a full fruit,<note place="margin">3. Cib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and full of this fruit muſt bee euery<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 20 Deut 11. 17 Luk. 19. 8. Ioh. 12. 3. 1. Sam 25. 18. Eccl. 11. 1.</note> branch. If thy enemy hunger, feede him: ſhut not thy hand from thy poore brother: but make a diuident of thy goods with <hi>Zache,</hi> an vnguent of thy oyle with <hi>Mary,</hi> a banquet of thy bread with <hi>Abiga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> Caſt thy bread on the face of the waters, to thoſe whoſe face is wet with teares, moyſt with waters. The Hebrew is <hi>Lachem,</hi> which is all ſort of fruite as well as bread: were it bread alone, then bread is <hi>Panis</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nis</hi> is <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> and <hi>Pan</hi> is all, meat, and drinke, and welcome withall, elſe it is as good not to giue at all. The Scripture doth<note place="margin">Way.</note> giue certaine cautions to direct our giuing. <hi>Eſt modus in dando, quid our,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quid.</note> 
               <hi>cui, quomod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quando.</hi> What muſt we giue? that which is ours; honour the<note place="margin">Pro. 3 9.</note> Lord with thy owne ſubſtance, and feede not the poore at anothers dore? for why ſhouldeſt thou be free on an others trencher. The diuell would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20343:32"/> giue all the world to our Sauior, (a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall almes but out of Gods Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quour) and <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. domin. 1493.</note> to Spaine, (a bountious Larges, but of the Indians freehold) and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a gentleman keepes a good houſe, when worſe then a Iew hee crucifies his tenants: for feeding at his wicket ſome poore that hunger, other poore are inforced to furniſh his dreſſer: ſay (gentle prouerbe) whether this bee not to rob <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why muſt wee giue? good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for as 1. God commands it, loue<note place="margin">Cur.</note> the ſtranger: the poore are ſtrangers,<note place="margin">Leu. 19. 34.</note> vſed ſtrangely, but then beloued, when releeued: and 2. Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it, <hi>Date Eleemoſynam:</hi> he that<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 11. 41.</note> giues you all requires your Almes: and 3. the ſpirit commends it: the<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 17.</note> poore to be fed, relieued, and eaſed, is an holy ſacrifice wherewith God is pleaſed: ſo 4. this the means to make you rich, the RR. ſay, tith and be rich, God ſayth, giue, and be rich; a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all argument, for ſhew mee that man that would not be rich, <hi>Et eris mihi
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20343:32"/> magnus Apollo,</hi> hath not the noyſe of earthly profit drowned the voyce of the heauently Prophet? each man almoſt imitates <hi>Ahab,</hi> lyes on his<note place="margin">1 Kin. 21. 4.</note> bed, turnes away his head, and will eate no bread.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther can ſleepie <hi>Morpheus</hi> cloſe his eyes,</l>
               <l>Leaſt <hi>Naboth</hi> fall, that hee, or his may riſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Yee Vineyard-mongers, come, and behold the ladder, <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, heauenly ſtayres, ſtayres to heauen, charity! now in time, get vp and climbe if you would bee wealthy: for he that giues to the poore, ſhall neuer be poore, hee that giues to the poore ſhall haue greater ſtore, like that cruſe of Oyle ſhall be more and more. <hi>Date &amp; dabitur, &amp; caput coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur,</hi> giue a croſſe, get a crowne,<note place="margin">Pro. 19. 17.</note> a purſe here, a kingdome after, <hi>Qui miſeretur, proximo foe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eratur domino:</hi> if you pitty the indigent, you lend to the omnipotent, and he becomes, as the poores ſurety, ſo your paymaſter: <hi>Non ad triplas, imo adce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuplas vſures.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:20343:33"/>
            <p>To whom muſt wee giue? feede<note place="margin">Cui.</note> not the Spaniel, I meane the fawning Sycophant, that (as one told Queene<note place="margin">S. W. R.</note> 
               <hi>Eliz.</hi>) will neuer ceaſe begging, while any continues giuing: nor the grayhound, the ryotous Prodigall, who will be ſo much the duller, by how much the fuller: nor the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiue, the gullet-theefe, who at the end of the tearm will be ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catechiſe thy purſe for an other boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: nor the Curr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the bawling ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, the hooke for him is the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt morſell: nor any other of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells whelps, that are ſick of that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nina appetentia,</hi> the greedy worme, Epicure, gluttons, belly-gods, whoſe onely ſtudy is to reade <hi>Apicius</hi> his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of the art of Munchery: no, no, giue not the childrens bread to theſe dogges: but when thou makeſt a feaſt, let the poore be thy gueſt: yet not Popiſh pouerty that is willfull<note place="margin">Luk. 14. 13.</note> iniquity: nor diueliſh pouerty grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the diuells bones, &amp; books, dice, and cards, wine, and women, and ſuch like husbandry: but inuite
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20343:33"/> to thy table ſuch as are Gods poore, whom the hand of the Lord hath brought to neceſſity, onely muſt theſe bee the obiect of our almes, while godly diſcretion is ſteward of our kitchin. <hi>Tribue illis diuitias tuas non qui phaſidem auem, ſed ſiliginis panem comedunt, qui famem expellant non qui luxuriam augeant,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How muſt we giue? let the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4. Quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi> 2. Cor. 9. 7.</note> direct. <hi>The Lord loueth a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giuer, (viz,</hi>) a giuer with a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye, no ſupercilious lowerer: 2. a cheerefull tongue, no ſeſquipedali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous brawler: 3. a cheerefull hand, no obnoxious retarder: to this end the oyle of our charity muſt bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded rightly. Shall I play the Druggiſt? God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to put into the holy oyle cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſpices: our almes muſt admit of<note place="margin">Exod. 30. 23, 24.</note> the like mixture. Myrrhe, a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liquor, that diſtills from the tree without cutting or inciſion: ſo muſt charity from vs without conſtraint or compulſion. Gods Almoner muſt not bee drawne like a Bare to the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20343:34"/> ſtake, a free-will offering, (be it but of ſome offall) is very pleaſing. 2. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon: which is hot in the mouth and ſtomacke too, ſo muſt we ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſtone-cold with <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al,</hi> nor luke-warme with <hi>Laodicea,</hi> but boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hotte with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> whoſe dayly practiſe was to feede, and releeue the poore him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. 3. <hi>Caſſia,</hi> as ſweete as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but a low ſhrub: the true <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme</hi> of humility: giue therefore, but not vaine-gloriouſly. Let not one hand know what the other hand<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 3.</note> doth doe: and giue not to men, to be ſeene of men, to be prayſed of men, for why ſhouldeſt thou trumpet out thine owne fame: if thou loue oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, God will vſe deteſtation, and thy ſoule finde deſolation. 4. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus:</hi> an odoriferous powder, but of a fragill reede: weake man, ſilly man, ſinfull man, no way meritorious. Then giue vpon earth, but think not thereby to purchaſe heauen, for when you haue giuen, when you haue done all that you haue, all that you can,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20343:34"/> you cannot but confeſſe you are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants. Therefore Saint <hi>Bernard, Periculoſa domus eorum qui</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in Pſal. qui habitat Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> 
               <hi>meritis ſuis ſperant:</hi> dangerous is their houſe that thinke to merit ſaluation by keeping of houſe, dangerous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ruinous. But leaſt I ſeeme tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, let vs conſider the time.</p>
            <p>When muſt we giue? <hi>To day if you will heare his voyce, harden not your</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quando.</hi> 5. Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>hearts,</hi> haue not hard hearts, be not hard-hearted. While you are aliue, ſee you relieue and looke that you giue while you liue, while wee haue time let vs doe good vnto all. Our<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> Sauiours action, muſt be our imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me while it is called to day,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9. 4.</note> for the night commeth (death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) when no man can worke. The poſthume-workes of many (making legacies of their wealth when they cannot keep it, and feeding the poore with a mould-meat at their doore) though it may profit the liuing, yet cannot helpe the dead; then benefite<note place="margin">Eccl. 14. 13</note> thy friend before thine end, and carry
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20343:35"/> not the candle, behind thy backe.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>With what, and why, whom, how, and when,</l>
               <l>Learne you to feede the ſonnes of men.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To harbour the ſtranger, is a <hi>Lot</hi>-like-fruite:<note place="margin">4. Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olligo.</note> two, or three Angels may beare him witneſſe. All Sodome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide could not ſhew ſuch an Apple, no not before it was watred with brimſtone, much leſſe ſince beeing <hi>mare amarum &amp; mare mortuum,</hi> a<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. deb. Iud. l. 5. c. 5. Corn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, hiſt. li. 5. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rab. li. 16. Plin. l. 5. c.</hi> 16. Iob 31. 32.</note> bitter ſea, a dead ſea, neyther giuing harbour to a bird, nor houſe-roome to a fiſh, nor welcome to any thing elſe that hath life: inhoſpitable churle, no ſuch churle <hi>Iob;</hi> the ſtranger did not lodge in the ſtreetes, but I opened my doore to the traueller: an open heart hath an open doore, and an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen mouth too, to language foorth a courteous inuitation, as come in thou bleſſed of the Lord, why ſtandeſt thou without. The fruite of this<note place="margin">Gen. 24. 33</note> fruit is ſweet, and odoriferous, for hereby as 1. man is eaſed: what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eaſe to a deuious traueller, then a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20343:35"/> bountious hoſt, or a knight hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar? Thus was the Thiſbite, eaſed by<note place="margin">2 Kin. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10</note> the Shunamite; ſo God, 2. is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: he that ſheets a bed for the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, layes a pillow for the head, and he that lodgeth a Chriſtian, entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Chriſt: thus Chriſt. He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth you (ſo pleaſing is hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that) he receiueth an Angell? yea<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 2. <hi>Aug. contra 5. hereſes.</hi>
               </note> me. <hi>Diſcite Chriſtiani, non indiſcrete exhibere hoſpitia, ne forte cui domum clauſeritis, ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſit Chriſtus:</hi> open the doore oh man with diſcretion, leaſt thou exclude Chriſt, while thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeſt a Chriſtian. 3. Wealth increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin">Pro. 11. 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kin. 17. 14</note> There is that ſcattereth, and more increaſeth: ſee the Sareptans barrell, the more is taken out, the more is put in. Poore <hi>Baucis</hi> inricht for har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Iupiter: Delos</hi> made firme land for entertaining <hi>Lato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a:</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6. 11</note> 
               <hi>Edome</hi> bleſſed for his gueſt the arke: <hi>Societ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te hoſpitis benefit hoſpiti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 3.</note> as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> preſence proſpered <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phars</hi> ſubſtance: and hee that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th a Prophet in the name of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſhall be rewarded with profit:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20343:36"/> 4. Heauen poſſeſſed: when I was a ſtranger, you receiued mee: what followes? therefore come you bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> of my Father, inherite the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you. Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith as much of <hi>Lot, Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cont. 5. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uaſit incend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, aeternum conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutus eſt praemium:</hi> the Angels were welcome to his houſe, therefore (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide temporall fauour) was hee wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to Gods houſe. But how are our Hoſpitalar knights chaſed from Rhodes? exil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d their aboades by that <hi>Ottoman</hi> horſe? The diuell that great Turke hath ſo lockt vp the gates of gracious Hoſpitality, that <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>-like wee preferre dogges before<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſter. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lib. 4. Pinner. re. camb.</note> men: and <hi>Cambaian</hi>-like haue hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalls for hawkes, when the feete of Chriſt muſt lodge in a barne, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not ſo warme: if our face be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ieruſalem, wee may trauell through Samaria, and no man inuite vs, nor ſhall we drinke at <hi>Iacobs</hi> well, vnleſſe ſome woman, ſome wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker veſſell of the poorer ranke, (for they that worſt may muſt carry the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20343:36"/> candle, and they that haue moſt, will giue leaſt) doe happe to giue it vs: though <hi>Peter</hi> bids vs bee harberous<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 8.</note> one to another without grudging.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Porter ſet open euery gate,</l>
               <l>That Chriſt may enter in thereat.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To cloath the naked, is a warme<note place="margin">5. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtio.</note> fruite. Begin at the beginning; it<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 21.</note> grew in Paradiſe: in the third of <hi>Gen.</hi> God had his wardrope, whence <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> bare <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> had all their accoutrement, skinnes of beaſts, (for their figge-leaues were not worth a figge) to couer their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</p>
            <p>And as he our Progenitors, ſo we our naked neighbours. Tis the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Chriſt, he that hath two coats, let him giue vnto him that hath none, giue him one. The Communion of Saints, fruit of our faith, part of our Creede. The practiſe of <hi>Iob,</hi> if I haue<note place="margin">Iob 31. 19, 20. 22.</note> ſeene any periſh for want of clothing, or any poore without couering, if his loynes haue not bleſſed me, and if he were not warnd with the fleece of my ſheepe, then let mine arme fall from
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20343:37"/> my ſhoulder-blade. <hi>Sic vos non vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis vellera fertis oues, Iob's</hi> ſheepe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cloathed him, and he cloathed Gods ſheepe.</p>
            <p>But now are our Cloathiers like our incloſers all for themſelues, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes contending who ſhall bee fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, I ſay not in a woollen liuery (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſome <hi>Iaſon</hi> array them in a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fleece) but in the Argonaut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuffe of <hi>D'dutramer</hi> brauery. I haue read of a Rabbin that aduiſeth hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to cloath themſelues beneath their ability, their children according to their ability, and their wiues aboue their ability: this laſt is good Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine much in requeſt (for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where the wiues backe pincheth the husbands belly) but we take not his counſell in that which is firſt, in that which is beſt for euery muſhroome (that is ingendered <hi>ex putredine,</hi> and crept but the laſt day out of the dunghill) will imitate <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gula</hi> in his change of ſuites, neuer wearing one twice.</p>
            <p>A new faſhioned blocke, a Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20343:37"/> locke, an Indian eare, a Spaniſh<note place="margin">Loue-lock taught the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nians by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. Ear hangd full of pearles.</note> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, a ſhort waſt (that no body now is a right Gallant) ruffe vpon ruffe, ſet vpon ſet, lace vpon lace, till the apparrell it ſelfe be alſo appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reld: <hi>Poccadillio's</hi> little ſinnes are layd aſide, and every man almoſt turned Ruffin (ſpecially if M<hi rend="sup">r•s</hi>. Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low be an hyred Laundreſſe) while <hi>Dauids</hi> meſſengers, and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours members, haue not a jag, haue not a rag, nor an Harrington in a bagge to hide their poſteriors. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitha Cumi,</hi> oh for ſome <hi>Dorcas</hi> to condemne theſe <hi>Ammons,</hi> and with the contrary vertue to ſhame theſe ſhauers.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Such garments as you haue in ſtore</l>
               <l>Make gard-ments for the naked poore.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To bury the dead is a liuing fruit,<note place="margin">6 Condo.</note> a fruite which the liuing muſt giue to the dead: when I am dead bury<note place="margin">1 Kin. 13. 31</note> me. If Bull's fleſh lye aboue ground<note place="margin">Lemnius.</note> and putrifie, it will ingender Bees, if Horſfleſh, Hornets, if Manſfleſh, Serpents: if ſo, neceſſity bids bury it, leaſt S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rpents ſting vs, and wee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20343:38"/> haue no Brazen Serpent to cure vs, if no, yet piety bids bury it, know you not that your bodies are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt? 'Twas piety in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> to bury the head, no leſſe in vs to interre the members: Cuſtome bids bury it. Though the old Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians<note place="margin">Herod. l. 3. porchacci funer. Anli. Elian. var. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. Solinus.</note> burned their dead corps (as the Romans had their vrne for their duſt aduſt) ſome <hi>Scythians</hi> hanged them vpon Trees: The <hi>Berb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccae</hi> in tombed them in their bellies: the <hi>Bactrians</hi> caſt them to their dogges: <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the ſixt baked his Cardinalls: <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogenes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serres.</note> wiſhed to bee devoured of Fiſhes: and diſſolute <hi>Mec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nas</hi> cared for no Funerall, careleſſely ſinging, <hi>Non tumulum curo.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>No graue for me when death cuts off mine age,</l>
               <l>The bird being flowne what matter for the cage?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Yet haue the Hebrews vſed to put earth in earth, that <hi>Cumulus ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris</hi> might bee <hi>tumul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s corporis,</hi> a<note place="margin">Gen. 25. 9 Ioſ. 24. 30.</note> heape of mould, a heape of mould, As <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Machpelah, Ioſuah</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:20343:38"/> in <hi>Tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>athſera,</hi> skuls in <hi>Golgotha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27. 33 Mat. 27. 7</note> and ſtrangers in <hi>Ace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dama:</hi> ſayth <hi>Iehu</hi> of <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> a wicked King of a Queene more wicked, viſite yonder<note place="margin">2 Kin. 9. 34</note> curſed woman and bury her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> curſed, yet buried. And what is the practiſe of the God-ſpels profeſſors, our ſtately Sepulchers with mournefull Elegies may bee vocall Expoſitors: Spice to imbalme it, ſheete to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrap it, Beere to ſupport it, porters to beare it, mourners to condole it, Bels to bewaile it, tombe to ingraue it, till the ſecond appearing of Chriſt ſhall reuiue it. Therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cals the place of buriall <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minatio</hi> in an aſſured hope of the reſuſcitation:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> A ſleeping place.</note> The Greekes <hi>Caemeterion,</hi> in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſiue confidence of a ioyfull reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, &amp; the <hi>Germans</hi> Gods-akre, as if it were hallowed for Gods habitation: though <hi>Iulian</hi> ſcoffe it as a campe of cottages. Indeede I confeſſe that pompous exequies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit but little deceaſed Carkaſſes, <hi>Nec</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ep.</hi> 92<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>magis ad defunctum pertinent homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quam ſecundae ad editum infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:20343:39"/> They ſee not our teares, heare not our cries, take no notice of our colours, whether they be blacke as in<note place="margin">M. <hi>Sandys.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Europe,</hi> or white as in <hi>Aſia,</hi> neither do our Bells skarre away the worms: <hi>Tamen inuenta eſt ſepultura vt viſu</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. fort.</note> 
               <hi>corpora, &amp; odore faeda amouerentur:</hi> Yet is the graue that which doth ſaue, not them from putrifaction, but vs from infection: So, it profits the living, hurts not the dead, therefore by the living muſt be giving to the dead. Nor haue we any that oppoſe this order but (that wandring Planet that will keepe no order, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſerues to be deprived of his orders) that curious, furious, injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous innovatorer, that being ſicke of Stoiciſme will not ſhed a teare, ſicke of Schiſme wil not read a prayer, nor meete the Corpes, nor bring it into the Church, nor ſay ought at the Graue, but like a Dogge or an Aſſe tumble the defunct into a ſqualled Ditch, as if it were <hi>Decorum</hi> to bury the dead <hi>Sepultura aſinorum,</hi> or as the <hi>Nabathaeans</hi> did their Kings in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20343:39"/> a Dunghill: <hi>Martin</hi> dye, and I will be thy Poet:<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Marc.</note>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Paſſenger, ſtay, read, heere lyeth.</l>
               <l>A Comet blazing with a glow-worme zeale,</l>
               <l>Pull'd downe from Heauen, with the Dragons tayle:</l>
               <l>Who when aliue did ſearch with ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble feete</l>
               <l>The ſtews of Amſterdam, now in a ſheete,</l>
               <l>Doth naked pae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance: gentle friends forbeare</l>
               <l>To wet his Tombe with any humid teare,</l>
               <l>Nor Funerall rite vnto his Carkaſſe giue,</l>
               <l>That gaue no Funerall rite whilſt he did liue:</l>
               <l>But let him haue when vitall breath doth paſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>The buriall of</hi> (Iehoiakim) <hi>an Aſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus for the body, ſhall we feede<note place="margin">Iere. 22. 19</note> the ſoule? our Buſh is not barren of Spirituall fruite: <hi>Cadit aſina et eſt qui ſubleuet; perit anima<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> non eſt qui reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitet:</hi> If a Beaſt but fall, we ſtriue to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20343:40"/> helpe it, when the ſoule is hungry, who would not feede it?</p>
            <p>To inſtruct the ignorant is a witty<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Inſtrue.</note> Fruite, the taſte of which Fruit muſt ſharpen our wit, elſe our beſt plea will be <hi>ignoramus: Alexanders</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age will not ſhine bright, vnleſſe <hi>Phyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as</hi> oyle it, nor the ſoule (Gods image) vnderſtand aright except ſome ſpiritual paedagogue inſtruct it. Can the knife cut without the whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone? The great <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gor</hi> tooke 30.<note place="margin">Relat. reg. mogor. Ioh. or.</note> children, kept them ſecretly, guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them cloſely, nurſed them ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, intending to ſerue what god they would ſerue: but neither could<note place="margin">Auth. grat. exem.</note> they euer ſpeake any word, neither would he euer ſerue any god.<note place="margin">Mich. Dray Bar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> war. cant. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>* Thus great wits forged into curious tooles</l>
               <l>Proue great wits oft to be the greatest fooles.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Surely nature is an Owle, &amp; were her neſt at <hi>Athens,</hi> had need of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles. We cannot come to Chriſt if the Father drawe vs not, nor do
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20343:40"/> any thing of our ſelues, if Chriſt helpe vs not: <hi>Faemina monetam non moneta faeminam,</hi> the woman found<note place="margin">Solinus.</note> the ſilver, not the ſiluer the woman: But as the Beare's Whelpe, is faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by licking: So is our ſoule new formed by ſchooling. Therefore a Word of the Maiſter, Scholler, School, Leſſon: 1. Let the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. be judicious, and able to teach:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>How can he write that's deſtitute of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inke?</l>
               <l>Or ſpeake a right that nothing right doth thinke?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Si Sacerdos eſt ſciat legem Domini, ſi</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. ſuper Agg. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ignoret legem D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mini ipſe ſe arguit non eſſe Sacerdotem Domini:</hi> Art thou a Teacher in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not theſe things? He that would haue a Teacher to bee a Knower, would not haue a Tutor to bee an<note place="margin">Iohn 3. 10.</note> Vnvnderſtander, leaſt the Blind, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Blind both be ditch'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities precedit lactationem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt conceiue before ſhe ſuckle, and they that will teach muſt bee, <hi>Doctorum Diſcipuli,</hi> before they be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20343:41"/> 
               <hi>Imperitorum Magiſtri,</hi> for how ſhould he teach the Accidens, that<note place="margin">Hier. ad Demetri.</note> hath not learned the <hi>A B C?</hi> 2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, and willing to practiſe, as<note place="margin">Greg. in Eze. hom. 1</note> 
               <hi>lampas</hi> a Torch to lighten others: ſo <hi>carbo</hi> alſo a Coale to burne to himſelfe, leaſt while the lippes relate knowledge, the hands bewray igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, no doubt but action is a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling inſtruction.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Segnius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rritant animos demiſſa per aures,</l>
               <l>Quam quae ſunt oculis ſubiecta fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus.</l>
               <l>A word in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare is ſuddenly forgot,</l>
               <l>When th'obiect of the eye evadeth not.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>For this cauſe would <hi>Auguſtus</hi> haue the Senators Children preſent in Court.</p>
            <p>Therefore thou that teacheſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſee thou teach thy ſelfe, and caſt not this <hi>item</hi> away, leaſt after all thy teaching thy ſelfe be a Caſt-away: why ſhouldſt thou bee like a Bell ſummoning others to the ſervice of God, and doing thy ſelfe no ſcruice
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20343:41"/> to God? or like that <hi>Beſtia Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copolae</hi> that <hi>Iulian</hi> twitted <hi>Auſtin</hi> with; a Beaſt pretended of great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ouer night, that ere morning was come, had devoured herſelfe: great bruite, ſmall fruite. But Chriſt taught as much by worke, as by word: and example ſpeakes after the Sermon is ended, euen after the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Let the Scholler be firſt, credulous to beleeu:<note place="margin">Scholler.</note> ſelfe-conceite may as well play the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>want as go to Schoole, hee that diſtruſts the Doctrine, ſhall want grace to proceede Doctor. <hi>Iſraell beleeued the Lord, and</hi> Moſes: <hi>and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the Diſciples heard, and beleeued the Meſſias:</hi> All thy hearing will do thee no good without beleeuing: a man may heare, and read, yet be a <hi>non proficient</hi> with-out a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reed, for can any one profit by that hee will not credit? Therefore let both people, and puple leaue vs, if they will not beleeue vs: for why ſhould our Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory aggravate their miſery in that day when the word which they haue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20343:42"/> heard (but not beleeued) ſhall iudge them? Yet we are no Rabbins, they<note place="margin">Sal. Iarch. in Deut. c. 17. 0. 12.</note> are peremptory, and thinke to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued though they ſay (as one ſayd) that the right hand is the left; or do as <hi>Hillel</hi> did, that one day taught his<note place="margin">Salm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rac. de Sab. Ignat. Lyolae epiſt. de obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. ad Frat. in Luſitan.</note> ſcholler, <hi>Aleph, Beth, Gimel,</hi> and the next day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Gimel, Beth, Aleph:</hi> nor are we Ieſuites to binde our audience to a blind obedience: me thinkes, this implicite faith, is explicite folly, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſay with Saint <hi>Bernard. Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum mandata non eſſe a ſubditis iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canda, vbi nihil iubere deprehendun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. Ep 7.</note> 
               <hi>diuinis contrarium inſtitutes, &amp;c.</hi> beleeue vs, onely ſo farre as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth ſecond vs, no further.</p>
            <p>Ingenious to conceiue, <hi>Quid abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> 
               <hi>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurdo canere?</hi> 'tis labor in vain to ſchool the deafe, &amp; as vain labor to teach the dolt. A foolelike <hi>Nabal,</hi> hath a heart like <hi>Nabal,</hi> a head like <hi>Nabal,</hi> a heart like a ſtone, a head like a ſtone: the ſtone is not ſenſible, nor he intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible.<note place="margin">Suidas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Like the foole <hi>Amphiſtides</hi> that knew not whether his father or mother brought him forth: or that<note place="margin">Perera.</note>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20343:42"/> ſimple Turke that could ſay no more for his Religion then this, <hi>Mahomet</hi> was a Moore, my Father was a Moore, and I am a Moore: ſo that we may ſay of him (as <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> of one like him) when he comes vnto vs, or ſits before vs, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one ſtone ſits vpon another.<note place="margin">apud Laer. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore pray vnto him who muſt bore thine eare, that hee will alſo bore thine heart, be an <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in this, <hi>Da mihi domine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d quod iubes, tun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iube Domine quicquid voles.</hi> Lord make mee conceiue what thou<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. Sol. 1.</note> Lord make mee conceiue what thou commandeſt, then Lord command me to doe what thou pleaſeſt. Studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to thriue: <hi>Non progred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediens:</hi> hee goes backward, that<note place="margin">3.</note> goes not forward. The Souldier in the campe muſt not alwayes reſt, there is a time when he muſt be tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <hi>Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c</hi> muſt not alwayes hang on the breaſt: there is a time when hee muſt be weaned. So the child of God (be hee but a petty) muſt ſtriue to thriue, that he may take out. It was <hi>Peters</hi> iniunction, (and if hee be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:20343:43"/> build vpon this) as new borne babes deſire the ſincere milke of the<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 2.</note> word that you may grow thereby.<note place="margin">Ber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fid. lib. 2.</note> If thou want growth, thou haſt no truth: for <hi>quomodo profic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſi tib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am ſufficis?</hi> he hath nothing learnd, that thinks him ſo learnd, he hath nothing<note place="margin">Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. nat. hiſt. l. 8. c. 25</note> to learne. The Crocodile is growing as long as breathing, bee thou lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as long as liuing.</p>
            <p>So Bookiſh was <hi>Socrates,</hi> that the Ecue of his death he would be taught muſicke, becauſe as hee loued lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and therefore liued learning, ſo he would dye learning: <hi>vita ſchola.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Schoole.</note> This life is a Seminary, this world a phrontiſtery, vniuerſe an vniuerſitie: into which we are admitted (being in the womb matriculated) like Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſophiſts naked: naked as of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward habiliments, (and ſo worſe then a beaſt, not hauing ſo much as <hi>ſitis, &amp; fames, &amp; fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gora poſcunt</hi>) of ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ornaments herein as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad as a beaſt, our ſole eye, the eye of our ſoule being put out by ignorance, a worſe diſeaſe then poxe or peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20343:43"/> But ſaith <hi>Dauid, Come hither,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>and I will teach thee the feare of the Lord:</hi> This world is a field whereon we muſt now, if euer, ſow: this life<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> a ſchoole wherein wee muſt now, if euer, know; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c erudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> poſtha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitio,</hi> therefore let vs conne our booke here, for <hi>ſtatutum eſt,</hi> I aſſure you wee muſt repeate our weekes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke hereafter.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Quod ſibi q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſque ſerit preſentis tempore vitae,</l>
               <l>Hoc ſibi m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit cum dicitur, it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> venite.</l>
               <l>That which is plowed, and ſow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſome,</l>
               <l>Shall be the crop when it is ſayd, goe come.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But we muſt goe and come from<note place="margin">Leſſon.</note> the ſchoole to the leſſon. Leſſe then one we cannot haue, and we need no more, if we learne this one †: Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſſe, God be my ſpeed, and well we ſhall ſpeed if ſcripture be lecture. <hi>Conſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum guber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aculum lex diuina:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> holy writ, muſt be the <hi>Adelantado</hi> of holy Church.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:20343:44"/>
            <p>Elſe the <hi>Armado</hi> of all our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is likely to haue a feelie hauen, <hi>Silla's</hi> haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: you erre ſaith Chriſt, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture: ignorance of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the mother of error: but <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Dominicum mare p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cificum</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Sayes are placable ſeas: oh Lord be my Pilot, and I feare no wracke: <hi>Dei doctrina v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i medicina<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches<note place="margin">Cryſ in ep. ad Col. c. 3. v. 16.</note> of God are the leſſons of men, <hi>anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pharmaca,</hi> the medicines of men: then ſpeake Lord, for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant heareth, thy ſcholler learneth.<note place="margin">Aug de bap cont. Dona. l. 6. c. 1.</note> Secular learning may bee an after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noones leſſon, <hi>in arundine ſterili ſole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vua pendere.</hi> A grape may hang on a fruitleſſe tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gge, and truth (in truth) is truth in <hi>Menander,</hi> as well as in <hi>Paul:</hi> But firſt of all, (ſaith the Son of God) ſeeke the kingdome of God: the kingdome of God is the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a ſauing leſſon, a Leſſon which will make vs wiſe to ſaluation. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Philoſophers, Poets, Orators, may like the <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptae</hi> amend our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions; but <hi>mors in olla, mors in olla,</hi> death in the pot, death in the pot, if
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20343:44"/> 
               <hi>Ezechiels</hi> ſalt doe not ſeaſon their broth, or <hi>Moſes</hi> his wood reliſh the marah of gentle learning. <hi>Hierome</hi> by an Angell was buffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed ſore, for ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying too much in heathen lore: but <hi>Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by an Angell was forced to eate the book which he brought him to be his meat.</p>
            <p>To correct the delinquent is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Caſtig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8.</note> 
               <hi>a bitter-ſweet:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Bitter in eating, for <hi>moleſtus eſt medicus fure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> phre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netico,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nif. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at.</note> 
               <hi>pater &amp; moleſtus indiſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to filio, ille ligando, iſte caedendo:</hi> the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion bindes, and the patient is tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, the father corrects, and the ſon is angry: and who but ſelfe-flaſhing Papiſts (that thinke the blood of calfes equiualent to the blood of Chriſt) is in loue with laſhing? Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily natures conſtitution cannot away with correction: are wee not all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to reproofe? it is a choak-peare, <hi>Monitores acerbi,</hi> they that tell vs of our faults are bitter to vs, <hi>Monitori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nal.</note> 
               <hi>aſperi,</hi> we that are faulty are no better to them, <hi>Gradere, fuge in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iudae,</hi> and open no more thy
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20343:45"/> mouth in <hi>Bethel. Bethel</hi> muſt onely eate <hi>placentia, Bethel</hi> muſt onely bee fed with pleaſings: but <hi>placentia fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia,</hi> pleaſings are leaſings, as <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae</hi> are cakes, and cakes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch ſpiced meate is nought for the ſoules ſtomacke. They that in a cup of gold drinke the poyſon of flattery, ſhall quaffe the gall of bitterneſſe in the Celler of miſery. But albeit reproofe be bitter in taſting, wee haue learned by proofe, 'tis ſweete in digeſting. And <hi>Dulcia non meruit qui non guſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit amara.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>He meriteth for euer to be ill,</l>
               <l>That doth refuſe to taſt a bitter pill.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Patient! a while be patient, and in fine, thou ſhalt finde it is the fineſt Phyſicke. <hi>David</hi> (ſicke of ſinne) was content to take it, willing to taſt it, could well digeſt it: let the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous (ſayth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he) reprooue me, not the Balmes of <hi>Gilead,</hi> much leſſe the Balmes of the wicked are halfe ſo precious. Therefore let euery one haue his <hi>Doſis,</hi> a word, or a blow, or a word, and a blow. If wording will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20343:45"/> ſerue, let not ſinners want it, thus the Lord, thou ſhalt in any wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thy neighbour. Tis as great an offence not to reprooue thy brother<note place="margin">Leu. 19. 18.</note> when he falls into a treſpaſſe, as it is (ſaith <hi>Rabanus</hi>) not to pardon him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rab. in Mat.</hi> 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when he askes forgiueneſſe.</p>
            <p>But to ſacrifice with hony in ſtead of ſalt, and to ſooth, and ſmooth when thou ſhouldeſt bite and ſmite, is <hi>offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re coccum ſed non bis tinctum, non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatum,</hi> to offer red, but not ſcarlet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig. in Exod.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the <hi>Die</hi> of thy words goes not deepe ynough, and if men dye for want of words, thine ſhall bee ſmart ynough. Cry, cry aloud, cry aloud and ſpare, lift vp thy words like a trumpet, &amp;c. But if words will not do, adde blows thereto. <hi>Grauiſſimus nodus in ligno,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 58.</note> 
               <hi>non poteſt expelli niſi grauiſſimo oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorio.</hi> An hatd knot, requires an hard knocke, a deſperate ſore, a deſperate<note place="margin">Ambr.</note> cure: <hi>Phineas</hi> his zeale, muſt vſe <hi>Phineas</hi> ſpeare, when ſinne is ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and cannot bluſh. But <hi>Fides ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in can. ſerm. 66.</note> 
               <hi>non imponenda,</hi> and ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>impetranda, non imperanda:</hi> faith
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20343:46"/> muſt be wrought rather by perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then by coaction. True! therefore we pronounce, peace, before wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce warre: <hi>Tamberlanes</hi> banners, white before red: many beeing like that Indian <hi>Lama,</hi> a ſheepiſh beaſt, that will doe more by intreaty, then<note place="margin">Huld. Sch. midel. c. 44.</note> by ſtripes twenty: therefore firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate; if that will not ſerue, thou mayeſt profitably beate. Speake to the eare, if the eare be deafe, ſpeake to the purſe, if that auaile not, ſpeake to the body, that the eare may ſay, I am inſtructed, purſe may ſay, I am impoueriſhed, body may ſay, I am a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>flicted, that eare, and purſe, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may ſay I am compeld, that the will of the Lord may be fulfilled, that the houſe of the Lord may bee alſo filled. Theſe tart corrections did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and reformd the Circumceli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">Aug. ad Vincent.</note> which when they did ſuffer, they began to conſider, whether they were ſcourged for matters of pietie, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corrected for tenents of obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie.</p>
            <p>The bridle (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20343:46"/> to the horſe, a whip to the aſſe,<note place="margin">Pro. 26. 3.</note> and a rod for the foole. Correct a wiſe man with a nod, a foole with a rod,<note place="margin">Pro. 17. 10.</note> yea with a club. If nodding will not ſerue nor breaking ſerue, it muſt bee a club, a hatchet, or a halter. Binde him faſt that hath a phrenſie, pricke him vp that hath a lethargie, leaſt our <hi>Salt—Peter—Rebells,</hi> keepe gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Reuels.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Where <hi>Mercury</hi> cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Mars</hi> bee there the Marſhall made.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Suſpende verbera, produce vbera:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Solare. 9.</note> hang vp your rods, hang out your dugges. To comfort the ſorrowfull, is a pleaſant fruite. The forbidden fruit was a fruit moſt pleaſant, though ignorance forbids me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry, or deſcribe it. The Cabaliſts thinke this fruit was grapes, ſo <hi>Ricci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: de Talm. do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Ara caeli. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. c. 4.</note> tells vs. <hi>Moſes Barcepha,</hi> not grapes, but wheat, ſo <hi>Boskier</hi> informs vs.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Druſius</hi> is confident, it was a figge; take his word for a payment:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20343:47"/> 
               <hi>Sane ficum fuiſſe illam arb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rem, cuius fructu illis veſci non licebat, non malum</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Druſ. de Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trag. cap.</hi> 4. Gen. 3.</note> 
               <hi>vt vulgus opinatur pia credidit anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas.</hi> Whatſoeuer it was <hi>Eue</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed it pleaſant to the eye, but this as more Cordiall, is pleaſant to the heart. The ſpirit of God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Comforter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, moouing in all, going through all,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 26.</note> therefore he is ſpirituall that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters comfort, and ſomewhat a kinne to the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Powr good Samarit an</l>
               <l>Th' Oylo of compaſsion into my wound:</l>
               <l>Mirth ecchos pleaſautly</l>
               <l>Where ſorrowes mightily late did abound.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Si paupertas angit, Si luctus maeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat, ſi dolor cordis inquietat, ſi vlla calamitas conturbat nos, aſſint bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Iob.</note> 
               <hi>qui non ſolum gaudere cum gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus, ſed etiam flere cum flentibus didicerunt: tunc aspera leniuntur, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſa ſuperantur, &amp; grauia releuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c.</hi> When pouerty pincheth me, or ſorrow deiecteth me, or hearts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>griefe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20343:47"/> afflicteth me, or ought thats ill troubleth me: oh for ſome friende, that ſinging when I am merry, and mourning when I am forrie, knowes how to bring ſweetely my pangs to an end. Giue wine to the ſorrowfull, comfort to the mournefull. Comfort my people: comfort <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Comfort one another. He that is in miſery hath neede of an Electuary:<note place="margin">Pro. 13. 1. Eſa. 40. 2. 1. Theſ. 4. 18 Iob. 6. 14</note> he that is afflicted, ſhould be pitied: whoſoeuer he be that is in the pit of oppreſſion, let him drinke with thee of the cup of conſolation. Sorrow is dry, and wants a comfortable health.<note place="margin">Ier. 16. 7. 2. Cor. 1. 3, 4</note> Hath not the Lord comforted vs, that we might be able to comfort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with the ſame comfort where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are comforted our ſelues?</p>
            <p>Now comfort is duple, as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect is double. <hi>Vnus duo,</hi> one man is two, body and ſoule: there is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort outward, and comfort inward. For that which is outward turne the leafe, and looke backward: we haue toucht it before, onely a word more. The imbroydred <hi>Lazar</hi> comes to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20343:48"/> thy gate, craues thereat not all but ſome, a pittance or crum, the froth or ſcum: giue him comfort.</p>
            <p>See thy ſelfe in him, and Chriſt in thy ſelfe. Behold I ſtand at the dore &amp; knocke, Oh ſend not away thy Chriſt with a mocke: do thou behold him, and hold it not from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtus petit (magna penuria) Chriſtus non accipit (magna iniuſtitia)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>vt habeas vnde luxurietur filius, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate careas vnde egeat Deus.</hi> Chriſt in the poore man asketh it of thee (great indigence) the poore man for Chriſts ſake gets it not from thee (great negligence) that thou by thy wealth ſhould make thy ſon a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton; while Gods Sonne in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers is ſuffered to want it. But ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall<note place="margin">2.</note> comfort is the ſpeciall comfort: let not the ſoule want this Antidote, <hi>a quo receſſit anima plangis corpus, cur</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>non &amp; animam a qua receſſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deus?</hi> thou mourn'ſt for the body when the ſoule is baniſhed, why not rather for the ſoule whence God is departed? <hi>Haeccine viſcera compaſſionis?</hi> are theſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20343:48"/> the bowells of Chriſtian compaſſion? for the paſſion of Chriſt, quench not the ſmoaking flaxe, breake not the bruiſed reede, but binde vp the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart, preach the Goſpell to the poore, that the children that ſit in darkeneſſe may receiue light. Let<note place="margin">Eſa. 9. 2.</note> this, or the like be thy Dialect. Poore ſoule! though thy ſinnes bee many, and therefore thy ſorrowes mighty, yet feare not the Lords fury, deſpaire not of Gods mercy. <hi>Iudas</hi> his deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration was worſe then his treaſon. Thou canſt not commit more then God can remit: his mercy tranſcends his workes, therefore thy works. His promiſe is indefinite to all. Come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me All, Whoores, Theeues, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> Vſurers, Purſe-cutters, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, Sodomites, Gomorrhaeans, Idolotars.</p>
            <p>Chriſt in his life rayſed three to life: the Rulers daughter, the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes<note place="margin">Luk. 8. 55. 7. 11. Ioh. 11. 44.</note> ſonne, and ſtinking <hi>Lazarus:</hi> one dead an houre, the ſecond a day, the third foure: reſembling three ſorts of ſinners, (all ſorts of ſinners:)
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20343:49"/> 1: in intention. 2. action. 3. dilecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Aug. de ver dom. ſer. 44.</note> Therefore thy ſinnes are not ſo deadly, but Chriſt can reſtore thee. At what time (what time ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer) a ſinner (what ſinner ſoeuer) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth of his wickednes (what wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe ſoeuer) the Lord will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get<note place="margin">Gloſ. in Ioel. 2.</note> any more to remember it, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gracious, and mercifull, <hi>Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus affectu, miſericors effectu</hi>) but will<note place="margin">Eſa. 40. 1.</note> remember for euer to forget it: and comfort ye, comfort ye: Oh how beautifull are the feete of thoſe that bring theſe glad tydings.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Sound vp the Dulcimer with glee,</l>
               <l>That drouping ſoules may merry be</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To pardon the offender, is a mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low fruit, and falls from the tree without plucking. Happy are they that eate it: happier they that beare it. Our bleſſed Buſh is ful of it: <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iunt perfecti viri in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriam diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mulare qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doque obliuiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i penitus &amp; donare, et ſi</hi>
               <note place="margin">Remitte 10. Sen. in Pro.</note> 
               <hi>neceſſe ſit in patientia ſupportare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A righteous man can diſſemble an iniury: ſometimes forgiue, and forget it wholly: and if need be, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it patiently.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:20343:49"/>
            <p>There be many ſtalkes on which this fruit growes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gods precept.</item>
               <item>2. Chriſts practiſe.</item>
               <item>3. Want of merit.</item>
               <item>4. Aſſurance of profit.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Muſt, for the King: the King of heauen tells vs we muſt, if euer flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh <hi>in anno gloriae</hi> beare this fruit <hi>in anno gratiae:</hi> thou ſhalt not reuenge thy ſelfe on the children of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (my people) for vengeance is<note place="margin">Leu. 19. 18. Rom. 12. 19</note> mine, and I will repay it (who dare preoccupate Gods prerogatiue?) It<note place="margin">Exo. 21. 24.</note> was once ſaide an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth: but <hi>Was</hi> is paſt, and<note place="margin">Mat, 5. 35.</note> the Canon is inuerted: a cheeke for a cheeke, a cloake for a ſtroake, a ſuite of apparrell for a ſute or a quarrell, a<note place="margin">44</note> kiſſe for a ſtabbe, a chalize for a chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge. Loue your enemies, we loue not aright if we pardon not iniuries: forgiue one another. The mandate of<note place="margin">Col. 3. 13.</note> the Almighty implies neceſſity. The ſonnes of <hi>Rechab</hi> would drinke no<note place="margin">Ier. 35. 6.</note> wine, becauſe their father forbad it; nor we wrath, becauſe our heauenly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20343:50"/> Father hath interdicted vs.</p>
            <p>The example of Chriſt inuites vs<note place="margin">2</note> to it. <hi>Si ſequi nequis pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cipientem, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere tamen antecedentem:</hi> if thou canſt not follow him that commands, follow him that obeyes: he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, reiected, wounded, bruiſed, oppreſſed, afflicted: They ſpit vpon him, that reſtored the blinde by his<note place="margin">Eſa. 53. 3. 5. 7.</note> ſpittle.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>His front with thornes, they ſharply crowne,</l>
               <l>Which (though they prickt it) would not frowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Strip him, whip him, All haile him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 22 Mat. 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 48. <hi>Pſeud. Sib.</hi>
               </note> nayle him. This gall was his meate, his drinke was vineger.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>But courſe his welcome wee may thinke:</l>
               <l>When bread ſo ſowre, ſo ſharpe his drinke.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>For all this hee opened not his mouth, I meane againſt them, but he opened it for them. Father forgiue them, they wot not what is done by them. All his reuenge was a prayer
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20343:50"/> againſt vengeance, writing in graſſe, what others in braſſe: wrongs. Are you wronged? Let not that minde be in you which is in Lions and L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pards: but let the ſame mind bee in you which was in Chriſt Ieſus, who being reuiled, did not reuile, being ſmitten, did not reſmite, &amp;c. <hi>Non qui</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>percutit, ſed qui reper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut it bellum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> Not he that ſends, but hee that accepts the challenge, makes the Duell.</p>
            <p>Gods child is ſenſible of his own<note place="margin">3.</note> blemiſhes. There is that in me which was not in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Sinn.</hi> I am conſcious of mine owne infirmities, deformities, I haue wrongd God, I haue wrongd my neighbour. My watch hath not beene well kept, for I haue miſpent my talent of time: my chimney hath not beene well ſwept, for the pot of my charity hath ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome boylde: my linnen hath not beene well waſht, for I haue not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed the naked mendicant: my ſoule hath not beene well ſcowrd, for I haue hated my brother in my heart:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20343:51"/> my hands haue not beene well pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for I haue iniured others: and it is <hi>lex talionis,</hi> if others doe ſo by me, Shall I ſeeke reuenge if God puniſh me? no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my wrongs to him haue deſerued it. Shall I bee witneſſe, Iudge, and hangman in mine owne cauſe, if another vexe me? No, hee is but Gods hammer, why ſhould I be like a dogge to bite at the ſtone, and not looke to the thrower? my wrongs to God ot him, to God and him doe merit it.<note place="margin">Grego. mor. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is patienter tollerat iniuriam, &amp; eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcit peccatis non parcere, qui apud Deum &amp; proximum multa quibus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti neceſſe eſt ſe recol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t comminiſſe:</hi> he cannot chooſe but take patiently, and forgiue freely (he muſt needes bluſh that doth contrary) ſuch offences as are offered him: that doth conſider how he hath offended his God aboue him, and his neighbours with him.</p>
            <p>Our ſinnes deſerue a <hi>mittimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4</note> paines without end, are our ſinnes ſtipend, it is Gods mercy that wee were not in the goale long ſince: but
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20343:51"/> if we will grant a <hi>Demittimus,</hi> and pardon others, God will pronounce a <hi>Remittimus</hi> and forgiue vs. <hi>Demit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, &amp; Demittemin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> it is his owne language; forgiue, and you ſhall bee<note place="margin">Luk 6. 36.</note> forgiuen. If you will forgiue men their treſpaſſes, your heauenly father<note place="margin">Mat 6. 14.</note> will forgiue you. Here is gaine, and great gaine indeed: <hi>Quare quis non fratri demittat parum, vt dignetur &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. Cath. conuerſat.</note> 
               <hi>dominus demittere totum?</hi> who would not forgiue a penny to be forgiuen a pound? thy brothers ſinne to thee is as a penny, thy ſinne to God as a pound; his feathers, thy lead, but this milne to ſmelt it.</p>
            <p>Theſe with others are the ſtalkes of this fruit: let them make thee, and me forbearing long ſuffering. Be not <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Diſciple to thinke it mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity to retaliat an iniury. Let not <hi>Scylla's</hi> Epitaph be ingrauen on thy graue.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Nemo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inimicus inferenda i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſuperauit.</l>
               <l>Here vnderneath this ragged ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Doth lye the corps of ſuch an one:</l>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:20343:52"/>
               <l>As neuer any could out goe,</l>
               <l>In taking vengeance on a foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Be not like that wild Iriſh, who would not haue the right arme of his child put in the font, leaſt being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated<note place="margin">M. <hi>Speede.</hi>
               </note> by water, hee ſhould not be able to execute his rancour: a true kerne, a true Carib: rather imitate that gentle <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that ſaid to <hi>Metel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Nunquam efficies vt iram Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris merearis,</hi> thou ſhalt neuer cauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> to bee angry with thee: rather imitate <hi>Marcus Cato,</hi> who ſayd to one that wrongd him, and cryed <hi>peccaus, non memini me percuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> I doe not remember that I was ſmitten: rather imitate bleſſed <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> who concerning <hi>Shimes</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uild him, ſaid let him alone, the Lord had bidden him.</p>
            <p>In the games of <hi>Olympus</hi> hee wan the prize that gaue the moſt blowes to his aduerſary: but in the liſts of Chriſt Ieſus hee gets the prayſe that puts vp moſt wrongs by an enemy. for God is his Agonotheta who will reward his iniury.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:20343:52"/>
               <l>Ecce quam bonum,</l>
               <l>Et quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucundum</l>
               <l>Eſt habitare</l>
               <l>Fratres in vnum.</l>
               <l>Good in it ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Fayre to the eye,</l>
               <l>Brethren to dwell</l>
               <l>In vnity,</l>
            </lg>
            <p>(<hi>i. e) Supportare oneroſum,</hi> to aſſiſt<note place="margin">Offer.</note> the helpleſſe, hapleſſe, and hopeleſſe, burdned, ouerburdned, with griefe and care cumbred, is a feeling fruit: feele the pulſe of a Chriſtian, his veines, are not vaine, but beare with compaſſion. <hi>Compaſſio, a compatior,</hi> therefore <hi>alter alterius onera portare,</hi> beare you the burdens one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">Gal 6.</note> and if an other greeue, <hi>diuidatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qualitèr,</hi> ſay halfe mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altera proſtratum corpus in ponte ita collocat vt altera inſiſtere proſtrato</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plinius.</note> 
               <hi>corpori, &amp; tranſire per illam poſſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Vpon a bridge two goates did meet</l>
               <l>So narrow that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Satyre feet,</l>
               <l>could not haue roome to tread,</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:20343:53"/>
               <l>One coucht him on his belly flat,</l>
               <l>That th'other might (admire therat) quite ore him be conuayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Here you heare of a Goate cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant: <hi>Moſes</hi> tells you of an Aſſe couchant, <hi>Iſachar</hi> couching between two burthens, not onely vndergoing his owne patiently, but bearing the burden of others feelingly. Good reaſon. Wee are members one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and muſt therefore yeeld ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention one to another.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>The outward members did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine,</l>
               <l>That they (forſooth) tooke all the paine,</l>
               <l>The idle belly to ſuſtaine with Dyet:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth one my friends I thinke it beſt,</l>
               <l>That neyther hand aboue the breſt,</l>
               <l>Once mooued be, if we will reſt in quiet.</l>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:20343:53"/>
               <l>This ſayd, and done, the body pynd,</l>
               <l>Seeing the members ſo vnkind,</l>
               <l>As to refuſe to feed and finde each other,</l>
               <l>Learne mortall man by what is ſaid,</l>
               <l>Thy loue be not confinde, and ſtayd,</l>
               <l>Vnto thy ſelfe, but helpe, and ayde thy brother.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Thou ſtandeſt in as much need of<note place="margin">2</note> him, as he of thee, and if ſo, 'tis but one good turne for another.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>A blind man once did ſue to wed,</l>
               <l>A woman that was lame:</l>
               <l>Saying their loue was firmely bred,</l>
               <l>Where wants were like or ſame.</l>
               <l>I cannot ſee ſhe cannot riſe,</l>
               <l>I lend her feet, and ſhe me eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But if thou haſt both eyes,<note place="margin">3</note> and feete, profit, and comfort now, thou knowſt not what weather 'twill be to morrow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tu quo que fac timeas, &amp; quae tibi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouid de pont.</note> 
               <hi>laeta videntar dum loqueris fieri triſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia poſſe putes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, feare while thou ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, leaſt thy ſweet to ſowre be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:20343:54"/>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth counſell it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thy ſelfe (ſaith hee) leaſt thou alſo be tempted. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> doth affirme it, ſpeaking of a brother that fell vnder the burden of ſome vice. <hi>Ille bodiè, &amp; ego cras:</hi> he to day, and<note place="margin">Ber. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. dom. Ser. 2.</note> I not vnlikely to fall to morrow.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>When griefe doth ſeaze anothers heart,</l>
               <l>Be thou content to beare a part.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Faithfull <hi>Oriſon</hi> is a fruit moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,<note place="margin">Oratio. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Orapronobis,</hi> ſayes the daughter: <hi>Oraprovobis,</hi> ſayes the mother: Daughter the ſoule, mother the Church, mother-Church, <hi>Quae ſi nil habeat dare, vult taemen or are,</hi> who ſhould ſhe be poore, and had nothing to giue vs, yet is ſhe too pure to ceaſe praying for vs: <hi>abſit a me hoc pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12. Iam. 5. 16.</note> let this ſinne (ſaith <hi>Samuel</hi>) be farre from me: hence the Apoſtle, pray one for another. When our bleſſed Sauiour had made his will, and bequeathed his mother to <hi>Iohn,</hi> his kingdome to a theefe, his coat to a ſouldiour, his body to the croſſe, his ſoule to hell for the redemption
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:20343:54"/> of mankinde, he prayed <hi>Pater ignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> forgiue them father: <hi>Frater dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſce,</hi> learne this brother: <hi>Tu non fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſi non orator,</hi> Thou art no brother, If thou pray not for another: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit faith ſaith, not <hi>Our Father,</hi> but <hi>my Father,</hi> as <hi>Thomas</hi> my God, and my Lord, ſince another mans faith cannot bee the Vicar of my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: yet prayer ſaith not onely, my Father, but our Father (euery man for himſelfe, and God for vs all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues to be curſed and anathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed of all) when you pray, thus ſay,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Paeter noſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Dauid</hi> played, the Diuell<note place="margin">1. Samuell.</note> would not dance, belike he liked not his muſicke: <hi>Saul</hi> was well rid of him, better was his roome then his company: when <hi>Moſes</hi> prayd, <hi>Iſrael</hi> conquered the Amalakites, as <hi>Gede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudges.</note> broken pitchers (broken hearts) and ſounding Trumpets (ecchoing<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. in Heb. hom.</hi> 27. 1 Samu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</note> lippes) chaſed away, and ouercame the Midianites. <hi>Certèmagna ſunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma oratio, ipſa bella <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uout prayers, are ſtrong ſpeares. Hereby
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:20343:55"/> the Patriarke preuayled with <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But perhaps you aske what others they are that muſt be prayed for?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer negatiuely: droppe not a bead, let no prayer bee ſayde for ſuch as are dead: they may be in thy Creed (for thou mayeſt hope well, that they are well) but take heede they come not into thy <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dirges, Maſſes, Tretalls, Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems, are to begge a pardon when the theefe is hanged, and after the faire, to vnpacke our ware. <hi>Medicus poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. in Mat. Hom. 75.</note> 
               <hi>aegrotus obijt nequicquam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe poteſt,</hi> in vaine is the potion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſſolution. If they be in heauen, they need not to vs: if in hell, there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great gulph twixt vs, and them, our prayer cannot goe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer for want of a bridge: <hi>Tertium penitus ignoramus, imo nec eſſe in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. cont. pelag. Hyp. lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctis inueniemus.</hi> There is no meane betweene theſe extreames: Purgatory is but imaginary: a Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Chimaera: a paper priſon, like the other Limbos, whereof <hi>Virgil</hi> (I
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20343:55"/> thinke) the heathen was one of the firſt builders: but Lord remember me now thou art in thy kingdome, and ſay to my Soule, it ſhall bee with thee in Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Doe not ſupplicate, for any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate:<note place="margin">2</note> There is a ſinne vnto death (to<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5. 16.</note> pray for it is as to pray for the dead) I doe not ſay you ſhall pray for it: the Prophet ſaith, You ſhall not pray<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. 16.</note> for it, to attempt it, is to tempt God: therefore <hi>Iudas</hi> gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> faire by his penſion, when he loſt the benefite of each good mans petition: bad husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, for halfe a crowne to exchange a crowne, for thirty pence of ſiluer, many talents of golden treaſure: hee may well hang whom no man ſpeaks for, no man prayes for.</p>
            <p>But (now affirmatiuely) except<note place="margin">2</note> before excepted, we are commanded<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 1 1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2 2</note> all to pray for all. Magiſtrates: bleſſe,<note place="margin">1</note> (bleſſed God) our gracious King<note place="margin">1</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> by thy grace, &amp;c. that as hee doth raigne by thee, ſo he may raigne for thee, that hee may raigne, and remaine perpetually with thee: Our
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:20343:56"/> hopefull Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> that no <hi>Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite</hi>
               <note place="margin">2</note> or <hi>Amorite</hi> may ſleepe in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but a true Iſraelite, that he may bee greater then great <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> on earth, and reſide, and abide aboue <hi>Charles-waine</hi> in heauen: The Count of <hi>Reyne</hi> his ſpouſe and progenie, that<note place="margin">3</note> againe they may raigne of account in <hi>Germany.</hi> And our <hi>Albion</hi>-Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators,<note place="margin">4</note> oh let them bee neither <hi>tranſ-nor Cis-Alpine-penſioners: &amp; ſic de caeteris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miniſters: we pray for you, pray<note place="margin">2</note> you for vs: <hi>Paul</hi> doth bid it: pray<note place="margin">Ephe. 6. 19 Act. 12. 5.</note> for me: the Church did it, for ſhee prayed for <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how is the world become a glutton? inſtead of praying for vs, prcying on vs? of 9284 <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,<note place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit. edit. vlt.</note> 3845 are become impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But <hi>quorſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c?</hi> our Belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god-patrons-latrons haue no eares for vs, nor prayers for vs.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt all finally pray for all generally, for Iewes and Pagans, Turkes, and Papiſts, though ſome Lincolne-ſhiere miniſters ſay ſuch a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:20343:56"/> petition implies a contradiction to particular election, that it would pleaſe thee to haue mercy vpon all men: yet in this alſo we beſeech thee to heare vs good Lord.</p>
            <p>Indeede ſuch charity is not to bee found in Popery: for when one <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> a Martyr did at the ſtake deſire<note place="margin">Act &amp; Men</note> the peoples prayers, <hi>Browne</hi> a Papiſt (oh pittifull Papiſt) ſayd hee would pray no more for him, then he would for a dogge. They haue Bell, Booke and Candle for vs, we a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Collect for them, that hauing but one ſhepheard, wee might all be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected into one fold: The Syrophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nician prayed for her daughter poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with a diuell, and wee for our brother be he neuer ſo euill.</p>
            <p>But how can any pray for others, that ſeldome or neuer pray for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh Lord thou knoweſt I neuer prayed before,</l>
               <l>But heare me now, Ile trouble thee no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:20343:57"/>
            <p>Quoth that ſea-faring paſſenger, when the ſtorme beate with anger, or how for others, and themſelues, that are full of vice, and fraught with ſinnes? If I regard wickedneſſe in<note place="margin">Pſal. 66. 18</note> my heart, the Lord will not heare me, <hi>Silete ne vos hac illi nauigare ſentiant.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Keepe ſilence ye, leaſt God doe ſee,</l>
               <l>You paſſe this way that ſinners be.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Then purge thy heart that God may heare thee, and pray for thy ſelfe, that others may be prayd for by thee.</p>
            <p>But happily it will be ſayd, I haue often prayd, yet finde no ayde: I and my brother <hi>periclitamur,</hi> are ſtill in danger. Fooliſh man, though thou be <hi>Popilius,</hi> God is not <hi>Antiochus: Popilius</hi> to <hi>Antiochus</hi> being ſent on a meſſage, drew a circle about his ſeat, adiuring him, ere he ſtird to anſwer his Embaſſage: but faith tarryes the Lords leaſure, and though the Lord tarry, it waytes his pleaſure. <hi>Is qui
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:20343:57"/> credit non prefeſtinabit,</hi> he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth maketh not haſt, when as he that beleeueth not maketh haſt, and hee that maketh haſt, maketh waſt: haſt, and waſt, are mother, and daughter, too haſtfull, and waſtfull, was <hi>Chone Hammigal,</hi> a Iewiſh <hi>Rabbi,</hi> who when the weather was droughty, put himſelfe in a Pye made fit for his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſaying, Lord of the world, thy childrens eyes are fixt on me, as one whom they thinke familiar with thee, I ſweare by thy name I will not out my Pie till thou grant them raine, here was fleſh in a Pie, but no ſalt, no wit.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Omniaſal ſapit, inſipidum caput eſt tibi Rabbi,</l>
               <l>Adde ſalem vt ſapidum ſit tibi Chone caput.</l>
               <l>In fine. Mutuall prayer procureth grace,</l>
               <l>When briniſh teares bedew the face.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>I am peruenimus vſque ad vmbeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martiall.</note> Let vs gather the fragments, the banquet is ended, and a rare one it
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:20343:58"/> were, were it well diſht: howeuer by ſuch as it is, you plainly ſee our Buſh is abounding with excellent fruite. Goe thou and doe likewiſe: Bring foorth (ſaith the Baptiſt) not flowers or flouriſhes, bloſſomes or ſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, buds or appearances, but fruits: not the fruite of the world, that's fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor the fruite of the fleſh, that is frailty, nor the fruit of the eyes, that is fancy, but meete fruites, meete for contrition of heart, reformation of life, ſanctification of Soule.</p>
            <p>Euen ſuch as are vicious, are very fructiferous, producing, and bearing, as greene fruits of imperfectneſſe: ſo red fruits of blood-thirſtines, yellow fruit of gall and bitterneſſe, flame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collourd fruit of drunkenneſſe, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colourd fruit of couetouſnes, pale-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord fruit of laſciuiouſnes: whoſe root is concupiſcence, Bole conſent, bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, bad deſires, buds, lewd words, flowers, vile actions, fruits, naughty cuſtomes; which the diuell doth plant, ſuggeſtion doth water, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance increaſe, neceſſity ripen, iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:20343:58"/> gather, and hell burne. Oh let not the children of this world, the brats of night, be wiſer and fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler then the children of light. Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one labour to bee like our Buſh, whoſe fruit is good, good and much.</p>
            <p>Be not an Oliue buſh (when the goates doe licke it fruitfulneſſe, doth leaue it) when others prayſe thee, let them not pride thee: bee not a vine buſh, (the more boughes, the fewer grapes) but if thou receiue more bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings from God, looke thou returne more fruit to God. Be not a Cloue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, (ſo hot by nature, and greedy of water, that it robbes it neighbours plants of moyſture) if thou haſt much be thankfull for it, if little, be content with it, and ſee thou doe not coue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an other mans profit. Why ſhouldeſt thou be like that Greene-land fowle (called an <hi>Allen</hi>) that (being of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power) beats the leſſer birds till they vomit vp their prey for him to deuoure, then diſmiſſing them with few feathers on their backes) leſſe meate in their bellies. I feare we haue
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:20343:59"/> in <hi>England</hi> too much of this fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, but be not thou ſo foule.</p>
            <p>In a word: if euer thy branches begin to wither, vſe <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt to make them proſper: (<hi>viz.</hi>) Cut the roote, put a ſtone in the cut, that the pure ayre may goe in, and groſſe humour flow out. Cutte the root, namely thy heart by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and true compunction: put in a ſtone, the remembrance of thy graue-ſtone, death, and diſſolution: that the groſſe humour, thy ſinnes by confeſſion may leaue thee, and the ayre of Gods Spirit, by deuotion fulfill thee, thus ſhall much and good fruit grow on thee: which gracious bleſſing that it may happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, I powre foorth my prayers continually to the Almighty. To whom be prayer now, and prayſe for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20343:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
